<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" type="xml"?>

<preface xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="acknowledgements">
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    
    <para>My apologies to anyone I leave out. This is a work built on the shoulders of many others;
        any mistakes are my own.</para>
    
    <para>I want to express my most profound gratitude to my wife, Cathi, not only for her excellent work
    on the Handbook itself, including editing, graphics, original articles, hours of printing, etc., but
    especially for not killing me during the course of the project.</para>
    
    <para>Thanks to Galen Chadwick and Denise Hay for submissions, footwork, comments, and typing,
    but also for hours of useful discussions and quite appreciated help with chores and farm work.</para>
    
    <para>Thanks to Marlene for much-needed typing assistence, especially for being an intermediary between
    Galen and the computer. Thanks to Denise and Marlene for transcribing Joe Maxwell's presentation on PODS.</para>
    
    <para>Jerry Diamond and Allen Busiek for excellent submissions. Allen especially for photos of his projects
    and an endless stream of informative emails. Jerry Diamond for his treasure trove of information in the
    Sustainable Cedar County group and occasional but very insightful comments on drafts.</para>
    
    <para>The Vimonts for information on useful farm products and for useful discussions, especially on
    Neighborhood Watch issues.</para>
    
    <para>Lincoln Justice for several excellent submissions (which I then edited mercilessly--- sorry!) and
    for very insightful and philosophical email discussions, for footwork getting this draft together, and for
    getting the ball rolling on making the Handbook site a general repository for WFNA writing material.</para>
    
    <para>To Deborah Snider for a couple of very useful submissions and, with Dave and Konner, help on the farm.</para>
    
    <para>To Canovi and Associates for legal information on self-defense in Missouri, including Frank and Mark.</para>
    
    <para>To everyone who released their work for use in the Handbook, especially Richard Moore and Travis Hughey.</para>
    
    <para>To everyone whose work I referenced, linked to, cited, or stole (with copyright permission, generally).</para>
    
    <para>To every volunteer who makes the WFNA possible.</para>
    
    <para>To Brian Highland and Hal Holiday, who taught me how to write and, more importantly, why.</para>
    
    <para>To the Adonai who gave me words and puts up with my frustrations. "And now remain these things: Faith, Hope, and Love".</para>
    
</preface>
