<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" type="xml"?>

<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="AlternativeEnergyAndLighting">
    <title>Alternative Energy and Lighting</title>
    
    <indexterm zone="AlternativeEnergyAndLighting">
        <primary>alternative energy</primary>
    </indexterm>
    
    <section><title>Energy and Lighting Resources in Springfield, Missouri area.</title>
    
    <section><title>Lighting</title>
    
    <para>Whenever an emergency situation hits, or even when the power just happens to go out for whatever reason,
        it's always a good idea to have some emergency lighting around the home. Remember when Y2K was about to hit and everyone was scrambling around for back-up generators to give them the extra jolt of power needed in case the end of the world did happen? Well, the end of the world didn't happen, but that doesn't mean it isn't a good idea to have a generator lying around the house. With that said, ask yourself, are you and your family ready for the next Y2K?</para>
    
    <para>It's always good to have some extra candles and flashlights around your home, but sometimes those items won't always suffice. A few other items you should also have on hand include water, batteries, and even some dry foodstuff; after all you never know how long you'll be in the dark for. Other items that I've found to be extremely helpful include hurricane lanterns and solar powered lights such as flood lights and lanterns.</para>
    
    <para><emphasis>Hurricane lanterns,</emphasis> whether they're the traditional ones made for oil candles or the modern ones that include flash bulb ballasts are excellent sources of light. Perfect for camping and emergency situations, hurricane lanterns provide a sufficient amount of light for long periods of time, which is surprising since it's considered a small lamp. Solar powered lights and flood lights also make for excellent emergency lights. Mainly used for industrial type projects, they can also be used for outdoor events and as construction lights since they're extremely bright.</para>
    
    <para>You wouldn't really think it, but solar powered lights do come in handy and require little maintenance. Batteries are usually not required (even though it's a good idea to have some around in the event that you do need them) and you only need to put them out in the sunlight to get them charged. Even today, many companies are developing solar powered and eco-friendly lights and flashlights, ensuring you that they will work the moment you need them. Regardless, no matter what the circumstances are, there's no such thing as being too prepared. As long as you have all the necessities, you'll be more than ready to face the situation head on.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Solar Lighting</title>
    
    <para><link xlink:href="http://www.ozarksgreenbuilding.com/lighting.html">http://www.ozarksgreenbuilding.com/lighting.html</link></para>
    
    <para>Lighting fixtures can account for nearly 20 percent of the electric bill in the average home. There are products out there, however, which use up to 50-75 percent less energy than the typical incandescent or halogen light fixture. Compact Fluorescent Light bulbs (CFL's) use about 1/4 the energy of regular incandescent bulbs to produce the same amount of light. They also last about ten times longer than regular bulbs, roughly 8-10 years. LED lighting is an emerging technology that holds great promise to revolutionize lighting over the next decade. They utilize about the same amount of energy as CFL bulbs, however have a much longer lifespan of about 22 years. LED lights also do not contain any mercury, one of the downsides of CFL bulbs. Here are some simple techniques to follow which can reduce the amount of lighting energy you consume in your home:</para>
    
    <para>Use task lighting to only illuminate the spaces you need, allowing you to reduce the wattage of light bulbs. 
        Take advantage of three way lights and dimming fixtures and use light light when you don't need it. 
        Install motion detectors on exterior lights so they aren't always on.</para>
    
    <para>Use low voltage lighting, such as CFL and LED lights wherever possible.</para>
    
    <para>Use solar lights for exterior landscape lighting which charge all day and do not require any electricity.
        For more information on lighting products, visit ENERGY STAR's lighting products guide. Look for ENERGY STAR qualified lighting fixtures when purchasing new lights.</para>
    </section>
        
    <section><title>Glade Winds</title>
    
    <para><link xlink:href="http://gladewinds.com/">http://gladewinds.com/</link> 
        Our Mission:  Educate our clients, local government and non-profit organizations on the benefits of clean, renewable energies.   Encourage sustainability so that our local communities will be self-sufficient and economically sound.   Provide our clients with quality products, consulting and installation that best suits their needs.
        GladeWinds’ expertise is with wind and solar technologies as well as organic lawn &amp; garden practices. We also know a thing or three about the hearth industry. Geothermal and Hydroelectric are other great alternatives to your energy needs. Call today!
        417-209-3227 or 417-209-3200</para>
    
    <para><link xlink:href="http://www.solarlightingusa.com/">http://www.solarlightingusa.com/</link></para>
    </section>
        
    <section><title>Power Source Solar</title>
    
    <para><link xlink:href="http://powersourcesolar.com/">http://powersourcesolar.com/</link> 
        Power Source Solar is the Ozark's largest and fastest-growing provider of electricity for boat docks, farms, government agencies, and homes.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section><title>LED Emergency Light</title>
    
    <para><link xlink:href="http://www.gilbertinc.com/gemini.htm">http://www.gilbertinc.com/gemini.htm</link></para>
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Transition Towns</title>
    
    <para>– preparing for a self-sufficient community-based future
        In over 150 cities in 14 countries, ‘Transition Town’ communities are raising awareness of the threats associated with peak oil and climate change, and taking practical steps to prepare for a post-industrial future…
        By Eartheasy Posted Nov 9, 2009</para>
    
    <para>While leaders in all levels of government discuss the realities of global economic distress, uncertain future energy supplies, and the overarching threat of climate change, a quiet evolution is making real progress in developing strategies to help us transform our communities to adapt to these upcoming challenges.</para>
    
    <para>In over 150 cities in 14 countries, ‘Transition Town’ communities are raising awareness of the threats associated with peak oil and climate change, and taking practical steps to prepare for a post-industrial future. And rather than dwell on bleak scenarios, participants in this grass-roots movement see future communities being more connected, more vibrant and more in touch with our environment than we see today.</para>
    
    <para>Each Transition Town is independent, developing its own plans and working on its own priorities. But the common denominator of all Transition Towns is a bottom-up, participatory process for all major decisions in each community.</para>
    
    <para>“If we collectively plan and act early enough there’s every likelihood that we can create a way of living that’s significantly more connected, more vibrant and more in touch with our environment than the oil-addicted treadmill that we find ourselves on today.”</para>
    
    <para>Transition Towns website
        Initiated by Louise Rooney and environmentalist Rob Hopkins in 2005, the “transition towns” movement is dedicated to drastically reducing carbon emissions on a local basis, developing alternatives to oil, and nurturing resilient local economies. Instead of looking to federal governments for money or leadership, transition towns are taking on the responsibility themselves. They are committed to working as communities to find new and better ways to live in harmony with nature while meeting essential needs.</para>
    
    <para>Dealing with the threats of peak oil and a changing climate requires fundamental change, beginning with the notion of individual ‘well-being’ as dependent on material acquisition. This entails redefining the very nature of community and culture so that people can move beyond the ‘infinite-growth’ economic model and begin to develop more locally based lifestyles that are more self-reliant, interdependent and meaningful.</para>
    
    <para>The key areas commonly examined are food, energy, transportation, local economics, communication, systems of care and the arts.</para>
    
    <para>Each Transition Town has its own priorities and issues it is working on. For instance, Multnomah County in Oregon has launched the Multnomah Food Initiative – a public engagement process that will bring the community together to create a shared vision, shared goals, and the first comprehensive community food action plan in the nation.</para>
    
    <para>The Transition Network suggests a list of seven principles of transition that enable a diversified response grounded in the local context. These are:
        <emphasis>Positive Visioning:</emphasis> Transition initiatives are based on a dedication to the creation of tangible, clearly expressed and practical visions of community life beyond dependence on fossil fuels. 
        
        <emphasis>Trust and Empowerment:</emphasis> Transition initiatives are based on telling people the closest version of the truth that we know in times when the information available is deeply contradictory, and then empowering appropriate responses. 
        Inclusion and Openness: Successful Transition initiatives depend on the unprecedented coming together of diverse sections of society. 
        <emphasis>Sharing and Networking:</emphasis> Information sharing and learning are key principles of resilient ecologies that are central to transition. 
        <emphasis>Building Resilience:</emphasis> How communities respond to shocks is critical to the transitional path beyond fossil-fuel dependency. The movement is explicit in its intention to build resilience across key economic sectors (including food, energy and transport) and across a range of appropriate scales – from local to national. 
        <emphasis>Inner and outer transition:</emphasis> Transition is a catalyst to shifting values and unleashing the energy and creativity of people to do what they are passionate about. 
        Subsidiarity: Self-organization and decision making at the appropriate scale are key principles drawn from resilient ecological systems.</para>
    
    <para><emphasis>“We truly don’t know if this will work. Transition is a social experiment on a massive scale. What we are convinced of is this: if we wait for the governments, it’ll be too little, too late; if we act as individuals, it’ll be too little; but if we act as communities, it might just be enough, just in time.”</emphasis></para>
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Del Tech Associates, Ltd.</title>
    
    <para>Distributor of materials and supplies for manufacturing solar panels and composites. 
        Business type: manufacturer, wholesale supplier 
        Product types: Specialty materials, process supplies for solar panel manufacturers and composites. 
        Address: 3598 E. Gasconade St. , Springfield, Missouri USA 65809 
        Telephone: 417-886-8281 
        Web Site: · <link xlink:href="http://deltechweb.com">http://deltechweb.com</link> 
        E-mail: ·   Send Email to Del Tech Associates, Ltd.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section><title>3M Industrial Tape &amp; Specialties</title>
    
    <literallayout>Business type: manufacturer 
        Product types: lightweight composite materials for electric vehicle chassis. 
        Address: 3211 E. Chestnut Expressway, Springfield, Missouri USA 65802 
        Telephone: (417) 869-5219
        Eagle-Picher Technologies, LLC (Commercial Products Department)
        Business type: manufacturer 
        Product types: sealed lead acid batteries, lithium batteries, rechargeable batteries, emergency backup batteries . 
        Address: P.O. Box 130, Seneca, Missouri USA 64865 
        Telephone: 417-776-2256 
        FAX: 417-776-2257
        Eagle-Picher Technologies, LLC
        Business type: manufacturer 
        Product types: specialty batteries, high purity gallium and germanium products, lithium-thionyl chloride batteries, valve-regulated lead-acid VRLA batteries. 
        Service types: power system design 
        Address: C &amp; Porter Streets, Joplin, Missouri USA 64801 
        Telephone: 417-623-8000 
        FAX: 417-781-1910</literallayout>
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Power Source Solar</title>
    
    <para>Business type: manufacturer, retail sales 
        Product types: alternative homes and buildings, solar pool heating systems, DC to AC power inverters, packaged power systems, photovoltaic systems, solar water pumping system components. 
        Address: 3718 Ponderosa, Springfield, Missouri USA 65803 
        Telephone: 417-833-4274</para>
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Sensible Steam Consultants</title>
    
    <literallayout>(Steam Engines)
        Business type: manufacturer, retail sales, wholesale supplier, service 
        Product types: wood fired steam powered electric generators, biomass energy boilers, biomass powered electric generators, packaged power systems, biomass energy products, portable power systems. 
        Service types: system design, consulting services, system installation 
        Address: 152 Von Goebels Lane, Branson, Missouri USA 65616 
        Telephone: 417-336-2869</literallayout>
    
    <literallayout>G &amp; S Associates
        417-725-1205
        997 Sterling Ct
        Nixa, MO 65714</literallayout>
    </section>
        
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Heating And Cooling in Emergencies</title>
    
    <section><title>Cooling Systems</title>
    
    <para>Earth Tubes non-electric, passive geothermal solar heating &amp; solar cooling systems for sustainable architecture 
        <link xlink:href="http://www.thenaturalhome.com/earthtube.htm">http://www.thenaturalhome.com/earthtube.htm</link> 
        
        home page » passive solar design chapter » earth tube detail page ... you are here Earthtubes (earthtubing) are, in a word, sustainable, non-electric, passive geothermal solar heating and solar cooling systems. Earthtubing utilizes conventional, thin wall, plastic pipe to passive solar pre-heat your home's air intake. Fresh air enters a system of these pipes which are laid around the interior of your home's foundation. You can let the air draft naturally through your earthtubes for a truly sustainable, non-electric, passive geothermal system or add fans and filters to supplement the home's back-up heating and cooling system. Be careful with Earthtube details, though ... while architects are warming-up to the idea, they are making very elementary mistakes, like using large concrete (cement) pipe that is impossible to clean. The Adolo Leopold Legacy Center earthtubing details are a classic example of very poor design that relies entirely upon mechanical means to attempt to clean the air coming out of the tempering tubes. Earth tubing (fresh air return tempering) is not suggested for low/zero energy, sustainable applications in humid climates where the designer is concerned about air quality. There have been numerous designs over the years that attempt to deal with the issues, but they invariably are forced to develop high-energy, mechanical systems to deal with lowering humidity and sterilize air prior to passage through the tempering earth tubes. Every low-tech passive energy system we have ever encountered fails to properly address the air quality issue. Hybrids tend to rely upon UV treatment of the air, which is sketchy, at best.</para>
    
    <section><title>Conventional Homes</title>
    
    <para>are typically High R value and "airtight", so all of the heating and cooling effect is stored within the air temperature (convection). If you let the air escape, you lose all your comfort. High thermal mass building materials allow the heating and cooling effect to be stored within the home's walls and floor (radiant). This allows you to vent the inside air of an HTM without "losing" all your heating or air conditioning comfort. Constant venting in the winter is common to HTMs, with fresh air being pre-heated or pre-cooled before it enters the home. Please note that Earthtubing is not meant as a summer cooling system in hot, humid climates where moisture would reach dewpoint and collect in the tubes. Weep holes are drilled in the bottom of corner fittings, but these drains can be quickly overwhelmed in a very humid climate. If you must alter your indoor climate in the summer for personal comfort level, you will need mechanical means. There really is no truly healthy passive method to de-humidify.     (Design Drawings and Plans follow)</para>
    </section>
        
    <section><title>Water Misting</title>
    
    <para><link xlink:href="http://www.rapidcool.net/?gclid=CLzVkv-Brp4CFRshnAodtR5umg">http://www.rapidcool.net/?gclid=CLzVkv-Brp4CFRshnAodtR5umg</link></para>
    
    <para>Water misting systems have proven to be more effective than conventional methods for cooling outdoor locations like a patio, green house, waiting line, or dining area. A mist fan system can increase productivity and employee morale in hot indoor or outdoor industrial working conditions.</para>
    
    <para>The concept incorporates water and heat to provide cooling through "flash evaporation". Specially designed mist nozzles operate under high pressure to produce tiny water droplets reducing the surrounding air temperature. Our custom stainless steel mistline provides cooling to the area from our high pressure pump assembly. When combined with mist nozzles, this mist system can achieve maximum cooling without wetting or residual moisture.</para>
    
    <para>Mister systems can also provide a dynamic visual effect to any home, patio, or commercial location. Rapid Cool offers one of the largest selections of mister equipment, fans, and components on the market today for home or commercial use. Whether it is one of our portable misting fans to a complete misting system, Rapid Cool can handle most any indoor or outdoor home, patio, green house, industrial, or commercial application.</para>
    
    <para>Quality systems for long life and trouble free operation
        For More Information or Price Quotes
        Call 800-573-4437 or Fill Out This Form</para>
    </section>
    </section>
        
    <section><title>National Affordable Housing Network</title>
    
    <para><link xlink:href="http://www.nahn.com/">http://www.nahn.com/</link></para>
    
    <para>We proved that low-cost housing for cold climates could be built to use less than 200 USD a year in space heat, while overall first costs were essentially the same as similar housing built without the efficiency features. The result was measured total house energy savings of more than 50 percent over current practice. Now, it's time to expand on this work and transfer it to those who need it most.</para>
    
    <para>The National Affordable Housing Network is working to dramatically change the way that affordable housing is built in this country. To achive these results, we:
        provide technical support and education to housing organizations serving the disadvantaged; 
        produce information products and communications support among energy practitioners to provide a way for non-profit housing organizations to get the help they need; 
        develop demonstrations of resource- efficient, affordable housing to provide verification of energy and resource efficiency measures; develop highly detailed, easy-to-follow houseplans and graphics to allow volunteers and self-help builders to follow step-by-step guidelines, while sharply reducing or eliminating marginal costs; develop partnerships between utilities and low-cost housing producers to design innovative low-income programs to help change practice; develop specifications and detailed guidance for adding efficiency in both rehabilitation and manufactured housing.</para>
    
    <para>Our highly detailed, easy-to-follow house plans and graphics allow volunteers and self-help builders to follow step-by-step guidelines, while sharply reducing or eliminating marginal costs.</para>
    
    <para>The National Affordable Housing Network (NAHN) was presented with the Andromeda Star of Energy Efficiency Award in recognition of its outstanding contribution to energy efficiency in the development of resources and technical assistance for construction of low-income housing in the United States.</para>
    
    <para>An independent, nonprofit organization, the National Affordable Housing Network represents the interests of low-income consumers in the development of highly efficient home building and improvement energy solutions. An emphasis on specific solutions for affordable energy design has resulted in methods that are documented, measured, and developed for households most in need of energy efficiency.</para>
    
    <para>The Network’s High Performance house plan series, designed for self-help builders in both warm and cold climates, helps reduce measured total house energy costs by up to 50 percent. With more than 23 years of field research, energy design and experience, NAHN experts have provided tens of thousands of individual contractors and builders with training and education on energy-efficient building practices. The Network also has a 12-year relationship with Habitat for Humanity, encouraging the organization to upgrade construction standards, providing research, evaluation and education as well as seeking additional resources for applied energy-efficient practices.</para>
    
    <para>What if some of the nation's leading resource and energy experts put their talents toward solving this problem? The result would be savings for disadvantaged families of from $500 to $1,000 a year, putting needed food on the table and clothes on children.</para>
    </section>
        
    <section><title>Backup Power and Cooling Plans for Critical Facilities</title>
    
    <para>Part 1: How One Hospital Improved Its Emergency Cooling Plan
        Part 2: Case Study: Hospital EPS Load Breakdown</para>
    
    <para>How One Hospital Improved Its Emergency Cooling Plan
        By Dan Koenigshofer
        May 2009
        <link xlink:href="http://www.facilitiesnet.com/powercommunication/article/How-One-Hospital-Improved-Its-Emergency-Cooling-Plan--10800">http://www.facilitiesnet.com/powercommunication/article/How-One-Hospital...</link></para>
    </section>
        
    <section><title>Efficient Heating of Commercial Space</title>

    <para>Large commercial buildings such as factories, warehouses, arenas, and aircraft hangars are difficult to heat due to their high ceiling and large air volumes.</para>
    
    <para>Forced air furnaces or unit heaters are the conventional approach but they result in large temperature differences and poor comfort.   Infrared heaters are more efficient at heating these buildings. These IR heaters use natural gas, electricity, or oil to heat the radiating surface. The heat is directed downward to the load, by line-of-sight and/or reflectors.</para>
    
    <para>The radiation warms occupants, objects, and the buildings floors and walls. Due to this direct radiant warming the indoor air temperature does not need to be set as high and hence the temperature difference and the energy consumption are reduced.</para>
    
    <para>The IES laboratory has an ongoing project which will compare three different space heating technologies: 
        * A low-intensity Infra-Red heater 
        * A single-stage condensing unit heater 
        * A single-stage non-condensing unit heater 
        The evaluation of these tests has included: thermal comfort calculations, steady state efficiency measurements, temperature profiles, and a comparison of heating degree day versus gas consumption.</para>
    
    <para><link xlink:href="http://canmetenergy-canmetenergie.nrcan-rncan.gc.ca/eng/buildings_communities/hvac_energy_systems/publications/200805.html">http://canmetenergy-canmetenergie.nrcan-rncan.gc.ca/eng/buildings_commun...</link></para>
    </section>
        
    <section><title>Zero-energy building</title>
    
    <para><link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zero-energy_building">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zero-energy_building</link> 
        
        A zero energy building (ZEB) or net zero energy building is a general term applied to a building with zero net energy consumption and zero carbon emissions annually. Zero energy buildings are autonomous from the energy grid supply - energy is produced on-site. This design principle is gaining considerable interest as renewable energy is a means to cut greenhouse gas emissions. Buildings use 40% of the total energy in the US and European Union.[1][2]
        Sunlight and solar heat, prevailing breezes, and the cool of the earth below a building, can provide daylighting and stable indoor temperatures with minimum mechanical means. Z.E.B.'s are normally optimized to use passive solar heat gain and shading, combined with thermal mass to stabilize diurnal temperature variations throughout the day, and in most climates are superinsulated.[5] All the technologies needed to create zero energy buildings are available off-the-shelf today.</para>
    
    <para>The Zero Energy Buildings Database is part of the High Performance Buildings Database which lists many additional projects. Visit the High Performance Buildings Database to discover more energy efficient building techniques. 
        <link xlink:href="http://zeb.buildinggreen.com/">http://zeb.buildinggreen.com/</link></para>
    
    <para>Annually, a Zero Energy Home produces enough energy to offset the amount purchased from the utility-resulting in a net-zero annual energy bill, sending the electric meter in reverse.</para>
    </section>
        
    <section><title>SOM Designs Zero Energy Chinese Skyscraper</title>
    
    <para>The 71-story, 2.2-million-square-foot Pearl River Tower, in the new city of Guangzhou, China, being built for the China National Tobacco Corp., is a “net”-zero-energy building designed by the storied architectural firm of Skidmore, Owings &amp; Merrill (SOM), New York City, scheduled for completion in 2009. The firm has set its sights on redefining one of its bread-and-butter project types, the corporate headquarters, into a model of high-tech sustainability</para>
    
    <para>The Pearl River Tower epitomizes the super tall corporate headquarters building of tomorrow as an iconic, high performance structure, that is designed so that it potentially produces as much energy as it consumes. The building’s form guides wind to a pair of openings at its mechanical floors. The winds drive turbines that generate energy for the building’s heating, ventilation and air conditioning systems. The openings also provide structural relief, by allowing wind to pass through the building instead of pressing against it.</para>
    
    <para>Continue reading "SOM Designs Zero Energy Chinese Skyscraper" »</para>
    </section>
        
    <section><title>Earth sheltered, Earth Berm and Underground Homes</title>
    
    <para><link xlink:href="http://www.coolhouseplans.com/links.html?searchCategory=Earth+Sheltered+Homes">http://www.coolhouseplans.com/links.html?searchCategory=Earth+Sheltered+...</link></para>
    
    <para>Earth sheltered homes became more popular in the 1970’s when energy efficient homes where in great demand, but have been around for centuries. Some advantages of an underground home are the energy savings and superior safety from some of nature’s fierce elements. These earth contact homes are billed as hurricane proof and tornado proof but not completely disaster proof. Also, if an earth shelter or underground house is built properly it is very earth friendly. Earth berm houses are some the environmentally or eco friendly homes on the market. On May 14th 1974 Malcolm Wells came up with Underground America Day and it has been celebrated every year since. It seems the biggest concern with this style of architecture is finding an underground house contractor. Below are some great resources for earth friendly sheltered living and green home contractors.</para>
    
    <para>PBS Performance Building Systems-earth sheltered-solar energy ...
        EARTH SHELTER CUSTOM HOMES Beautiful, Protective, Efficient ... When sheltered with earth, the home benefits from the constancy of the earth's temperature, ...
        
        <link xlink:href="http://www.earthshelter.com/">www.earthshelter.com/</link></para>
    
    <para>See more  energy effieient home desings in the section on  SHELTER</para>
    </section>
        
    <section><title>Wood stoves</title>
    
    <para><link xlink:href="http://www.woodheat.org/technology/woodstoves.htm">http://www.woodheat.org/technology/woodstoves.htm</link></para>
    
    <para>A wood stove is the most popular, flexible and economical wood heating option. A stove can be located almost anywhere there is enough space and where its chimney can be properly routed. A perfect installation has the stove located centrally in the main floor living area of the house and the flue pipe running straight up into the chimney. This installation design will provide the best performance and need the least amount of maintenance.</para>
    
    <para><emphasis>Wood stoves are for space heating</emphasis>
        
        A wood stove is defined as a space heater and space heaters are intended to heat a space directly, unlike a central heating furnace, which supplies its heat to the house through a system of ducts. But because modern houses conserve energy more effectively than older houses and need less heat to stay warm, it is now possible to heat an average-size modern home with a single space heater, provided it is located in the main living area.</para>
    
    <para>If you want to heat most or all of your house with a wood stove, try to meet these two objectives: First, the heater should be located in the area where the family spends most of its time. And second, there should be ways for the heat to flow to other parts of the house. These conditions are not usually difficult to meet, but they do need to be planned.</para>
    
    <para>Put the stove in the area you spend your time.
        Choosing the right location for the stove may be the most important decision you must make. The heater should be located in the part of the house you want to be the warmest. This is usually the main floor area where kitchen, living and dining rooms are located and where families normally spend most of their time. By locating the space heater in this area, you will be warm and comfortable while you eat meals and relax.</para>
    
    <para>For heat upstairs, don't put the stove in the basement
        A basement is not a good location for effective space heating. Although the heated air from the stove does tend to rise to higher levels of the house, this movement is normally too slow and limited to provide comfort on the upper floor. Usually, in an effort to keep the main floor living spaces comfortably warm, the basement is overheated. This wastes fuel and the frequent high firing can damage the stove. Unfinished basements are particularly bad locations because too much of the heat is absorbed by the walls and lost to the outside. Also, wood stoves operating in basements may over-fire or smolder without anyone noticing. The basement is only a good location for a space heater if your family spends much of its time in a basement family or recreation room.</para>
    
    <para><emphasis>Stove heat output versus room size</emphasis> 
        If your house is divided up into small rooms you will probably not be able to heat it entirely with a single space heater. A stove too large for the room it is in will overheat the space quickly.</para>
    
    <para>Houses of open plan design with fewer separations between rooms can be heated entirely with a space heater, depending on their size and energy efficiency. In an open plan house, a larger appliance can be used without overheating the space.</para>
    
    <para>Correct stove sizing is important because a stove too large for the heat demand of the space will be operated with slow, smoldering fires much of the time to avoid overheating the room, and an undersized stove can be damaged by frequent over-firing to keep up with heat demand.</para>
    
    <para>A wood heat retailer is the best person to advise you on stove sizing for your home. Since experienced retailers know the performance of each stove, they can help you match a stove to your heating objectives and the location you have selected for it. When you visit a retail store to look over the available options, take along a floor plan of your house. This will save time and help the salesperson give you better advice.</para>
    
        
    <section><title>Stove structural design</title>
    
    <para>Some aspects of the design of wood stoves are related more to looks and personal preference than to performance. For example, there is no functional difference between cast iron or plate steel construction, and painted or enameled finishes. These differences affect appearance and cost but not heating performance.</para>
    
    <para>Although the bottom and rear of all new stoves are shielded to prevent overheating of the floor and to permit close clearances to combustible walls, some stoves have shielded sides and top as well. The more shielded a stove is, the more of its heat is delivered to the room by warm air convection than by direct radiation from the hot stove surfaces.</para>
    
    <para>Some specialists say that fully shielded stoves are better for small spaces because the hot air they produce more readily travels to other areas and because they don't feel as hot when you sit near them. In practical terms, however, most modern stoves have both radiant and convective characteristics.</para>
    
        
    <section><title>Combustion design</title>
    
    <para>The internal design of wood stoves has changed entirely since 1990, as the result of the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency regulation established in the late 1980s. The EPA's mandatory smoke emission limit for wood stoves is 7.5 grams of smoke per hour.  Today, all wood stoves and fireplace inserts, and some factory-built fireplaces sold in the U.S. must meet this limit. Stove manufacturers have improved their combustion technologies over the years, and now some newer stoves have certified emissions in the 1 to 4 g/h range. The EPA certified emission rate is a reliable number that can be compared from one model to the next, but a one or two gram per hour difference in smoke emissions does not mean much in day-to-day use.</para>
    
    <para>The two general approaches to meeting the EPA smoke emission limits are catalytic and non-catalytic combustion. Both approaches have proved effective, but there are performance differences. In catalytic combustion the smoky exhaust is passed through a coated ceramic honeycomb inside the stove where the smoke gases and particles ignite and burn. Catalytic stoves are capable of producing a long, even heat output. All catalytic stoves have a lever-operated catalyst bypass damper which is opened for starting and reloading. The catalytic honeycomb degrades over time and must be replaced, but its durability is largely in the hands of the stove user. The catalyst can last more than six seasons if the stove is used properly, but if the stove is over-fired, garbage is burned and regular cleaning and maintenance are not done, the catalyst may break down in as little as two years.</para>
    
    <para>Non-catalytic stoves do not use a catalyst, but have three internal characteristics that create a good environment for complete combustion. These are firebox insulation, a large baffle to produce a longer, hotter gas flow path and pre-heated combustion air introduced through small holes above the fuel in the firebox. Non-cats cannot match the even heat output of catalytic stoves, but their owners love watching the beautiful fire they create. The baffle and some other internal parts of a non-catalytic stove will need replacement from time to time as they deteriorate with the high heat of efficient combustion.</para>
    
    <para>Although most of the stoves on the market are non-cats, some of the most popular high-end stoves use catalytic combustion. Because they are slightly more complicated to operate, and the best of them do produce exceptional performance, catalytic stoves are suited to people who like technology and are prepared to maintain it properly so it continues to operate at peak performance. Both options have their pros and cons, and most users of either type seem satisfied with the performance of their stoves.</para>
    
    <para>![Catalytic Stove]</para>
    
    <para>Cross section of a catalytic stove, showing combustion air/exhaust flow patterns, the catalytic element and the bypass damper.</para>
    
    <para>Cross section of a non-catalytic stove, showing combustion air/exhaust flow patterns, large baffle and high level combustion air supply.</para>
    </section>
        
    <section><title>Why advanced stoves are worth the extra cost</title>
    
    <para>On average, advanced, EPA certified stoves are about one-third more efficient than the old box, pot belly, or step stoves, and almost all of the currently available central wood heating furnaces and boilers. That’s one-third less cost if you buy firewood, or one-third less cutting, hauling and stacking if you cut your own. Although this higher efficiency is a by-product of mandatory emissions limits, it has made the EPA rules a winner for both the environment and stove users. The extra cost of advanced technology is about \$200 per stove. Over just two seasons of wood burning the greater efficiency of the stove will more than compensate for the higher initial cost. 
        Advanced stoves produce about 90 percent less particulate matter - smoke - than older stoves. After a fire is ignited, you should see no visible smoke from the chimney, so neighbors won't complain and the foul smell, and thick smoke won't blanket your yard either. 
        Fires ignite more easily and burn more completely in these new stoves. The result is a far more convenient and pleasurable wood burning experience. 
        Virtually all the new stoves have a glass panel in their door and an air-wash system to keep it clear. This not only means being able to monitor the fire and adjust it periodically to get a perfect burn, but the fire itself is spectacular to watch. No fire in a conventional stove or fireplace can compare with the beauty of an efficient wood fire.</para>
    
    <para>Ninety percent less smoke means 90 percent less creosote. This gives two important benefits. First, the chance of chimney fire is virtually eliminated, as long as the stove is operated correctly and reasonable maintenance is done. And second, the flue pipe and chimney will need cleaning much less frequently, which is another way the new technology stoves save time and money.</para>
    </section>
        
    <section><title>Hybrid Stove Making Charcoal</title>
    
    <para>Biomass cooking stove burns wood to charcoal and saves the charcoal. One pound of wood cooks 6 kiols of rice and makes 65 grams of char
        <link xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BGXv7buNUMY">www.youtube.com/watch?v=BGXv7buNUMY</link> -     VIDEO
        <link xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BGXv7buNUMY">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BGXv7buNUMY</link></para>
    </section>
        
    <section><title>WOODGAS AND ROCKET STOVE PRINCIPLES</title>
    
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>AVAN STOVE - 
            N. Sai Bhaskar Reddy,GEO GEOECOLOGY ENERGY ORGANISATION, December 30, 2007</para></listitem>
        
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>Avan (Earth) Stove 
        <link xlink:href="http://e-avanstove.blogspot.com/">http://e-avanstove.blogspot.com/</link> 
        has the features of both Rocket stove and Woodgas stove. It is made up of 25 nos of ordinary bricks, four bricks with slits, one piece of flat tile, one steel grate 7x7 inches and Clay mixed with cow dung. The approximate cost of construction is $ 2 (USD). All types of biomass can be used as fuel (Sticks / twigs / chips of wood / dry leaves / grass / saw dust / cow dung cakes / paddy husk etc.) and advantage of gravity is used for easy and semi-automatic feeding. Designed by Dr. N. Sai Bhaskar Reddy, GEO -Geoecology Energy Organisation <link xlink:href="http://www.e-geo.org">http://www.e-geo.org</link> declared as Creative Commons.</para>
    </section>
    </section>
        
    <section><title>More Woodstove Magic</title>
    
    <para>by Daryle Thomas
        I hate to get off on the wrong foot. So let me offer a bit of opening advice: "They ain't nothin' magical 'bout burnin' a woodstove."</para>
    
    <para>That takes a big load off of my mind. Should anything I say in the next few lines strike you as a trifle abnormal, you may rest assured that it is only the perception of abnormality. No magic, no hocus pocus. Operating a woodstove is simple, straightforward and easy.</para>
    
    <para>How many times have you heard the phrase "airtight woodstove?" Talk about the perception of abnormality. There is not, nor never has been, any such thing as an airtight woodstove. Think about things that are airtight. A Volkswagen Beetle floating on a pond. The refrigerator on the back porch. A vacuum. But not a woodstove. Air has to be going in to make the fire burn.</para>
    
    <para>Understanding that the stove is only as good as the chimney is a necessary perception with wood heat. In simple terms, if the smoke is going up the chimney, it won't be coming out into the room.</para>
    </section>
        
    <section><title>Burning Issues in Wood Burning</title>
    
    <para>A German physicist named Fahrenheit developed a temperature scale on which water freezes at 32 degrees and boils at 212 degrees. The book, Fahrenheit 451, touches on the priceless information that, if one wishes to burn a book, one must heat the book to 451 degrees F.</para>
    
    <para>Years ago, as a fledgling Boy Scout, I would bet my fellow scouts all the money in their pockets that I could boil water in a newspaper cup over a campfire. Soon all the money in their pockets was in my pocket. The perception that the paper cup would catch fire is every bit as erroneous as thinking green wood burns.</para>
    
    <para>Any chemist will tell you that all the water must be consumed before the paper will heat up past 212 degrees. Since the paper won't ignite until it is heated over 450 degrees, the water will boil before the paper burns. Guess what happens to green wood? Green wood is up to 50 percent water. That's right, campers. All the water must be boiled out of the wood before the remaining fibers will be heated to their ignition point. Just like the paper cup, the temperature of the wood will not rise above 212 degrees until the water is gone. Bear in mind that creosote forms at temperatures below 300 degrees F. So while you are most assuredly not burning the green wood, you are producing creosote.</para>
    
    <para>While we're at it, dry wood doesn't burn, either. It sublimates. Say what! Next time you haven't got a great deal to do, watch what goes on in the wood stove carefully. If you look closely, you will see that the flames don't actually touch the wood! The stick of wood is the storage chamber for volatile gases.</para>
    
    <para>When the wood is heated well into the 450 degree range, these gases are driven off and ignite. After all the volatiles are driven off, the wood becomes charcoal. Charcoal is flammable, which is why it glows red in the firebox.</para>
    
    <para>When all that can burn in our once handsome chunk of wood has burned, we are left with ash. Some ash is required to insulate the hot coals and preserve them for the morning reload. Too much ash chokes out the fire, and must be removed. A sure sign of too much ash is the inability to place more than two tiny pieces of wood into the firebox. Do yourself a favor and take out the ash.</para>
    
    <para><link xlink:href="http://www.ruralvermont.com/vermontweathervane/issues/winter/97012/dthomas97012.shtml">http://www.ruralvermont.com/vermontweathervane/issues/winter/97012/dthom...</link></para>
    </section>
        
    <section><title>Gallery of Cooking Stoves:</title>
    
    <para>Gallery of Current Work (2002)
        <link xlink:href="http://www.repp.org/discussiongroups/resources/stoves/gallery.html">http://www.repp.org/discussiongroups/resources/stoves/gallery.html</link></para>
    </section>
        
    <section><title>Improved Cookstoves and Charcoal Production</title>
    
    <para>-- <emphasis>"The Appropriate Technology Sourcebook: A Guide to Practical Books for Small Community Technology"</emphasis> by Ken Darrow and Mike Saxenian, revised and enlarged edition, 1993, Consortium for Sustainable Village Based Development (CSVBD) ISBN 0917704185. This section of the Sourcebook has reviews of 37 books on improved cookstoves and charcoal production covering all aspects of the subject from design to community acceptance, along with a concise but thorough 1,000-word overview of the problems, constraints and solutions. It includes some wise cautions. For instance, you might assume that the less smoke the better, but you might be wrong: "In many places, smoke from indoor cooking fires is a significant contributor to lung and eye disease. Yet this smoke also serves to dry crops hung over the cooking area and to protect thatched roofs from insect damage". It's best to assume that your assumptions could be wrong. The reviews are pithy and to-the-point, with sources for the books and prices. Reading the whole section (about 8,000 words) will give you a good introduction to this promising but far from simple field of work. Online at publishers Village Earth/CSVBD:</para>
    
    <para><link xlink:href="http://www.villageearth.org/pages/Appropriate_Technology/ATSourcebook/Energycookstoves.php">http://www.villageearth.org/pages/Appropriate_Technology/ATSourcebook/En...</link></para>
    
    </section>
    </section>
    </section>
</article>
