<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" type="xml"?>
<preface xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
        xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
        xml:id="forward">
    <title>Forward</title>
    <subtitle>A BIOREGIONAL APPROACH TO RESTORING FOOD SECURITY</subtitle>
    
    <para>Galen Chadwick, Regional Coordinator WFNA</para>
    
    <para>First of all, this Handbook was conceived as a gift to the people of 
        Missouri, to freely address an astonishing proposition: We, the people, 
        can no longer independently feed ourselves. By any measure, not one Show
        Me county is still self-sustaining, much less able to supply a diverse 
        quantity of home grown food for our teeming cities. Not even close.</para>
    
    <para>Within living memory, a localized food supply system was the norm all
        across America. Thousands of resilient, often vibrant, local economies 
        were built upon it. People knew their neighbors and, by and large, 
        trusted each other to do the right thing. As little kids, we biked all 
        over town without a second thought. Crime was low; people had time for 
        each other. But now, everything’s turned upside down. The handshake, 
        Main Street community of my youth has vanished, along with our national 
        food security and countless jobs. What happened?</para>
    
    <para>Our heritage of self reliance and economic independence has mutated 
        into a state of globalized dependency. The Jeffersonian dream of an 
        agrarian commonwealth has soured into a Hamiltonian nightmare. Historic 
        factors are many, but beginning in the late 1960’s, structural collapse 
        became systematic and intentional. Please see films like <citetitle pubwork="film">The Future of 
        Food</citetitle>, <citetitle pubwork="film">Food Inc.</citetitle>,
        <citetitle pubwork="film">The World According to Monsanto</citetitle>,
        <citetitle pubwork="film">Fresh</citetitle>, <citetitle pubwork="film">The End of 
        Suburbia</citetitle>, <citetitle pubwork="film">Food Matters</citetitle>,
        or <citetitle pubwork="film">Dirt</citetitle> if you still have any doubt about this.</para>
    
    <para>At the household level, marketers strive day and night to program us 
        with the logic of fast-food, microwave “efficiency.” But the arc of <glossterm>monological</glossterm>
        consumerism has also funneled extraordinary power to those at the top 
        end while destroying the family commercial farm at the bottom. 
        Industrialized agriculture has dispossessed millions of family farmers 
        into our cities, the largest human migration in history. “Rural 
        cleansing” is the term the corporados like to use.</para>
    
    <para>It gets worse: according to world food statistics, some 96% of all 
        fruit and vegetable varieties grown a century ago- the people’s 
        commonwealth of millennia- has gone extinct <citebiblioid>1326</citebiblioid>.
        We now suffer a breakdown of continuity so profound, a cultural amnesia
        so incalculable, we have no name for it. Surprise! You now work for the
        Global Casino, are owned by foreign banks, and China “feeds the world.”</para>
   
    <bridgehead renderas="sect3" role="highlight"><quote linkend="Forward_FeedOurselves"
        >What problems might confront the 320 million consumers of America
        <emphasis>if we had to feed ourselves again</emphasis>?</quote></bridgehead>
    
    <para>And so here we are. The offshore, just-in-time globalized delivery 
        system means only 2-3 days of food is in the pipeline on any given date 
        (FEMA estimate).
        Our lives now depend upon an uninterrupted flow of cheap Mid East oil. 
        Question: Where, in this post 9/11context, do our notions about
        “<glossterm>sustainability</glossterm>” fit if we can’t feed ourselves?
        <phrase xml:id="Forward_FeedOurselves">What problems might confront the 320 million consumers of America
        <emphasis>if we had to feed ourselves again</emphasis>?</phrase></para>
    
    <para>These questions matter because the last Americans able to feed 
        themselves without Big Government, Big Oil and Big Pharma are pushing 80
        to 90 years old. Don’t we boast that there are certain jobs “that 
        Americans no longer do?” But the downside is never quite spelled out, is
        it?</para>
    
    <para>The Well Fed Neighbor Alliance’s answer begins with a 20 year plan 
        for restoring food and economic security for some million residents of 
        S.W. Missouri. Our bioregional approach includes 30 contiguous counties 
        that surround the urban hub of Springfield. The interface between the 
        Ozark highlands (woodland) and the Osage Plains (prairie) is our 
        bioregion; the conditions, opportunities and obstacles often vary 
        greatly from state to state.</para>
    
    <para>In his Introduction, computer wizard Eric Vought explains his 
        Wiki-inspired creation and how to ground your overall security needs in 
        everyday practicality. The links he provides are not meant to be a 
        compendium, but rather to initiate a document you can continue to fill 
        and modify any way you like. Like a country potluck, take what suits; or
        add more of your own and leave the rest for others.</para>
    
    <bridgehead renderas="sect3" role="highlight"><quote linkend="Forward_RegionalPlan">A
        regional plan requires the creation of an economic locomotive 
        powerful enough to make everything work, and it must be smart enough to 
        resist corporate take-over and/or Federal animus.</quote></bridgehead>
    
    <para><phrase xml:id="Forward_RegionalPlan">A regional plan requires the creation of an economic locomotive 
        powerful enough to make everything work, and it must be smart enough to 
        resist corporate take-over and/or Federal animus.</phrase> To this end, Joe 
        Maxwell’s invention of a <glossterm>Producer Operated Distribution System</glossterm> 
        (P.O.D.S.), combined with the expertise of co-op builder Russ Kremer, 
        formed the heart of our working co-op structure. With this vertically 
        coordinated farm-to-consumer value chain (open books system) we aim to 
        establish trust at the bedrock level. Everybody knows what everybody 
        makes, and everybody helps the others to prosper. We must grow local, 
        buy local, bank local.</para>
    
    <para>Structurally, the Well Fed Neighbor Coop is a for-profit center that 
        operates under the WFNA Ltd., a 501 C3 educational nonprofit. The Coop 
        functions as a central broker for all commercial parties. It offers 
        insurance protection, product differentiation, consumer loyalty, and 
        point-of-sales marketing that the big box firms can’t match. This Coop 
        model can be tailored to fit the unique circumstances of other 
        communities. But it is probably not for everyone. Restoring a regional 
        food supply system is a heavy lift.</para>
    
    <para>The Coop is a pull-through distribution model that brings higher 
        value to the producer, transporter, processor, cold storage operator, 
        grocer, customer, restaurant and ultimately, to large institutional 
        providers. Independent supermarkets want a variety of meats, proteins, 
        dairy, eggs, veggies, fruits, herbs and all kinds of value added 
        products that come from our region. Everything comes down to building 
        demand.</para>
    
    <para>To fill these needs we’ve established mutually binding contracts, and
        our producers must also sign best-practices pledges. Customer 
        involvement is proven to increase with in-store CSA’s (Community 
        Sponsored Agriculture), producer field audits and tours, WFN Coop 
        co-branding, and our WFNA seal of quality approval. The Co-op acquires, 
        protects, promotes, and differentiates local products.</para>
    
    <para>There are several positive aspects to this legal arrangement, and Joe
        Maxwell and Russ Kremer were hired for their professional expertise at 
        the formative level. Obviously, investment planning, SEC rules, and 
        funding for an effort of this magnitude requires team depth and 
        professional involvement. We’ve learned that “build it and they will 
        come” attempts at Coop building usually fail, more so when attempting to
        wrestle formidable economic realities.</para>
    
    <para>Beyond Coop formation, the range of Alliance volunteer activities is 
        impressive. Our <phrase xlink:href="http://wellfedneighbor.ning.com/group/1000gardensproject/">1000
            Gardens Project</phrase> gave us almost instant “movement” 
        status. The goal was to inspire the creation of 1000 urban gardens 
        between our official launch, (on Jan 3rd 2009), and approaching Earth 
        Day, April 22nd. Given the huge national trend, we managed to help 
        instigate some 3,500 new gardens in about 100 days. Local nursery sales
        <emphasis>doubled</emphasis> over the previous year.</para>
    
    <para>Another ally, <phrase xlink:href="http://wellfedneighbor.ning.com/group/momsforlocalfood">Mom’s
        for Local Food</phrase>, is reaching into hospitals and 
        schools with nutritional education and introducing the “lunchbox 
        rebellion.” Sending kids to school with healthy, locally grown food is 
        the fastest way to keep the nano tech and GMO garbage where it belongs, 
        i.e., rotting in warehouses. Women make or influence around 93% of all 
        food purchase decisions<citebiblioid>1328</citebiblioid> and 
        our Moms are continually hitting grocers and restaurants with demands 
        to stock local products. Mom’s recently sponsored a well attended 5k 
        run, and more fun activities are planned.</para>
    
    <para>The Gateway Farms permaculture program is restoring an abandoned, 15 
        acre, hardscrabble farm. A country-savvy couple is developing an 
        extensive produce garden and experimenting with a number of familiar and
        exotic crops. In addition to hosting a parade of visiting volunteers 
        and frequent canning parties, they tend a small experimental pecan and 
        paw paw orchard, make hay, and raise bulls, chickens, rabbits, ducks and
        miniature pigs.</para>
    
    <para>Several larger farms have joined us in helping urban folks make the 
        transition to a prosperous and independent ag-based future. We aim to 
        restore the diverse, independent commercial family farm model from the 
        Golden Age of Missouri Agriculture, while applying the best science of 
        today. No one is interested in drudgery! Note: According to bankers, 
        Missouri’s most profitable farms (non-corporate, non-subsidized), are 8 
        to 10 acres, often with niche crops or raised bed/greenhouse operations 
        based on Joel Salatin’s Polyface Farm Model<citebiblioid>1327</citebiblioid>.</para>
    
    <para>A ministry component is in the works. Call it "Noah's B&amp;B" for 
        now, the idea is for young urban families to visit rural congregants and
        stay with the farm faithful once a month or so. This will help revive 
        our ageing, crossroads churches, bring a little income to our struggling
        farms, while helping our kids to learn the lessons of self-sufficiency.
        By collecting eggs, helping with gardens, tending livestock, and 
        learning the daily chores, they will keep alive our hopes and dreams for
        freedom.</para>
    
    <para>A student group, Guerrilla Gardeners, is starting up as of this writing. Other
        organizations frequently collaborate with the WFNA wherever food and job restoration is
        a mutual mission. Check out our social website,
        <link xlink:href="http://wellfedneighbor.com/">wellfedneighbor.com</link>
        to meet a rapidly growing collection
        of exceptionally informed, caring people. A well-fed belly begins with a well-fed
        heart!</para>
    
    <para>We make no claim to knowing all the answers. Indeed, our first 
        objective is to simply buy time. No one can foresee all the changes that
        a comprehensive and coordinated transition to “<glossterm>sustainability</glossterm>” will
        bring. But however the word may eventually be defined, we can all agree
        the first step is to create a diverse and prosperous regional food 
        supply system, one capable of feeding all of us indefinitely. Restoring 
        statewide <glossterm>energy sovereignty</glossterm> sufficient to achieve this end is a logical corollary.</para>
    
    <bridgehead renderas="sect3" role="highlight"><quote linkend="Forward_SpeakingToSovereignty">Speaking
        to this sovereignty, the silence of our politicians and academicians is deafening.</quote></bridgehead>
    
    <para><phrase xml:id="Forward_SpeakingToSovereignty">Speaking to this sovereignty,
    the silence of our politicians and academicians is deafening.</phrase>
        Aside from the private views of a few friends
        employed by the Extension office, we hear only crickets. Why is this? 
        Because the attainment of a sustainable, prosperous, and peaceful 
        future--- while not theoretically impossible—-- would almost 
        certainly not support the <emphasis>status quo</emphasis> interests of our leading institutions.
        Truth be told, the dark side of this discussion includes almost all of us.</para>
    
    <para>Perpetual resource extraction, farm labor exploitation, limitless
        construction and the industrialized food system fill certain functions 
        essential to societal stability. Until other ways of filling them are 
        developed, the real job of our institutional elites is to maintain— and 
        improve— the effectiveness of globalization. Do we really want 
        “sustainability?” It is not so obvious. Missing is any context for 
        realism, beginning with objective measurements for governmental and 
        institutional accountability and performance.</para>
    
    <para><emphasis>We can not independently feed ourselves.</emphasis> What does this 
        imply? Some say the situation is intractable from the top down, but the 
        general reader may be equally unprepared to face some unsettling, 
        personal conclusions. Restoring a food secure future goes waaaaay beyond
        putting in squiggly light bulbs and inflating tires to a proper 
        pressure. Most urbanites expect convenience at every step, view the raw 
        physicality of farm life with gimlet-eyed suspicion. “You want <emphasis>ME</emphasis>
        to sweat all day over a few grubby carrots? Are you crazy?” To be 
        perfectly blunt, restoring a food secure future requires an 
        across-the-board awakening: No Food = You’re Screwed.</para>
    
    <para>Our prototypical, “single bottom line” mentality is profoundly 
        reductionist. But for a few exceptions it frames the national debate and
        it frames us. Green wash and eco-positivism notwithstanding, our 
        paycheck silently argues that poverty is necessary and desirable, and 
        that our military extravagance should continue to function as a social 
        welfare institution in exactly the same sense as our rest homes, 
        hospitals, schools and prisons.</para>
    
    <para>Conventional green projects often showcase institutional concern, 
        while deflecting the energy of those pressing for real action. Creating 
        lasting structural change is not the goal. A genuinely sustainable, 
        inclusive, and peaceful world will require radical, individual 
        reinvention. We must return to work the land in significant numbers. 
        Otherwise, we will simply mill about at the exit of history, 
        directionless.</para>
    
    <para>The WFNA policy is to screen all partisan commentary from our website
        and activities. Inside the garden gate, ideology offers no vision or 
        plan for a sustainable future, only the need for self-revelation. Those 
        who inhabit the upper half of the bell curve get this. Please help us 
        keep it that way.</para>
    
    <bridgehead renderas="sect3" role="highlight"><quote linkend="Forward_InSum">In sum,
        the Handbook provides the missing context of realism for 
        establishing authentic “sustainability”.</quote></bridgehead>
    
    <para><phrase xml:id="Forward_InSum">In sum, the Handbook provides the missing context of realism for 
    establishing authentic “sustainability”.</phrase>
        Squiggly light bulbs and thicker insulation in the attic are irrelevant, in the end, unless based
        upon a restored, bioregional food supply system sufficient for the 
        people living in that region.</para>
    
    <para>Self-governance and the sovereign right to determine our own vision 
        of the future, to secure our rights and defend them, means we must again
        grow, own, trade, and transport our own food within a privatized, free 
        market system.</para>
    
    <para>To this end, the WFNA champions a peaceful, inclusive, prosperous, 
        and sustainable economy built upon food independence, and upon energy 
        sovereignty sufficient to guarantee it. Feed Missouri first! Every 
        lesser goal is derivative and futile until food security is restored.</para>
    
    <para>This Handbook is dedicated to all who yearn for a compelling, 
        comprehensive, and coordinated vision of a free America. We seek 
        independent, generous, entrepreneurial people. As WFNA president Ruell 
        Chappell says, are you ready to put “real skin in the game?” Ready to 
        vote three times a day with your fork? Civilization, after all, is only 
        three meals deep.</para>
    
    <para>The WFNA Handbook is meant to be used in any way that helps bring us together. The remaining way forward is simple if not easy:
        <emphasis>redeem the land if we ourselves would be redeemed</emphasis>. This hope compasses the essence of our motto:</para>
    
    <para>“The best defense against hard times is a well-fed neighbor”</para>
    
    <para>Kind regards.</para>
    
    <para>Galen Chadwick</para>
    
</preface>
