<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" type="xml"?>

<preface xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="LegalNotice">

    <title>Legal Notice</title>
    <para>The County Restoration Handbook (hereafter "the Handbook") project 
        is a collaborative effort of several organizations and combining of 
        information from <emphasis>many</emphasis> people. As such, the contents of
        the Handbook is not to be considered official policy of and may not have 
        been approved by its member organizations, including 
        <link xlink:href="http://wellfedneighbor.com/">The Well-Fed Neighbor Alliance</link> and <link xlink:href="http://thestatesmen.org/">The Statesmen For Our Constitutional Republic</link>.
        Inappropriate content should be brought to the attention of the project
        administrators through any of the various commenting and discussion 
        mechanisms on the Handbook site or via email to the 
        <link xlink:href="mailto:webmaster@thestatesmen.org">webmaster</link>.</para>
    
    <para>Mail may also be sent to:
        
        <address>
        <orgname>The County Restoration Handbook Project</orgname>
        c/o <personname>Eric Vought</personname>        
        <street>14280 Lawrence 1050</street>
        <city>Stotts City</city> <state>MO</state> <postcode>65756</postcode>
        <country>USA</country>
        </address></para>
    
    <section><title>Copyright and License of Contributed Work</title>
        
        <para>Copyright of any contributed work vests in the original author. 
            Authors contributing content grant the Well-Fed Neighbor Alliance and 
            The Statesmen For Our Constitutional Republic a perpetual, worldwide, 
            non-exclusive, transferable, royalty-free license to distribute the 
            content in any media for the purposes of this Handbook, including the 
            right to create derivative works. It is our policy to maintain a history
            of contributions so that credit can be given where due.</para>
        
        <para>All text in the Handbook or on the Handbook website is made available to
            others under a <link xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">Creative
                Commons Attribution-Share-Alike 3.0 Unported License</link>. To view a
            copy of this license, visit <link xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/" >http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/</link>
            or send a letter to:
            
        <address>
        <orgname>Creative Commons</orgname>
        <street>171 Second Street, Suite 300</street>
        <city>Sam Francisco</city> <state>California</state> <postcode>94105</postcode>
        <country>USA</country>
        </address></para>

        <para>This license allows you to freely 
            redistribute content and create new derivative works as long as you
            
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem><para>credit the original source and</para></listitem>
                
                <listitem><para>make the derivative available under 
                the same terms as you received it.</para></listitem>
            </orderedlist>

            If a contributed work was from the 
            public domain or exists outside the Handbook under a more permissive 
            license, or you obtain permission directly from the original author, you
            may have additional permissions with respect to the work.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Contribution Guidelines and Abuses</title>
        
        <para>It is the intent of this project to highlight best practices, working
            from existing information wherever possible. This will often result in a
            Cite And Summarize policy of summarizing important details and citing the
            original sources for more information. Copyrighted work shall
            <emphasis>not</emphasis> be wholesale copied into the Handbook without permission of the original author.</para>
        
        <para>If you are a copyright owner and believe your work has been copied or
            plagiarized, whether intentionally or unintentionally, please flag such
            violations through any of the available comment or discussion 
            mechanisms available on the Handbook site or through email to the 
            webmaster. Properly prepared DMCA take-down notices should go to
            <link xlink:href="mailto:webmaster@thestatesmen.org">webmaster@thestatesmen.org</link>
            and will be responded to as promptly as possible in a volunteer 
            organization. In cases where there is controversy over the content, this
            may require coordination with leadership of the Well-Fed Neighbor 
            Alliance, so your patience is appreciated.</para>
        
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Limitations of Liability, Caveat Lector</title>
        
        <para>Neither the Well-Fed Neighbor Alliance nor any contributor to this 
            project, including The Statesmen For Our Constitutional Republic, are 
            liable for the accuracy of the content. We are attempting to make 
            existing information available in a convenient form. Mistakes in 
            compiling the information are the fault of the Handbook authors, not the
            original authors, however, mistakes <emphasis>will</emphasis> occur. We make
            no representation that this information is perfect, and in fact, it is a 
            constant work-in-progress. The reader is admonished to do their own 
            homework and take advantage of the
            <link linkend="Bibliography">Bibliography</link>
            in carefully evaluating the information presented here. We are in
            <emphasis>no way</emphasis>
            responsible for intentional misuse of Handbook contents.</para>
    </section>
</preface>
