<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" type="xml"?>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="LevelsOfDetailOverview">
    <title>Levels Of Detail Overview</title>
        
    <para>The handbook covers several levels of detail and several overlapping goals as shown in the following diagram:</para>
    
    <figure>
        <title>Detail vs. Need Matrix</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/detailvneedmatrix_0.png"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    
    <para>People coming to the County Restoration Handbook may be approaching it from any of several points of view,
        from the individual family or farm level all the way up to county-level policy planning.
        The Handbook is organized roughly among these levels of detail with each main article marked according to the
        level(s) it pertains to as well as the level of need (see <link linkend="LevelsOfNeedOverview">Level of
        Need Overview</link>).
        This will eventually result in the equivalent of marked walking trails through the Handbook for particular audiences.</para>
    
    <para>We are specifically looking at three main levels of detail.</para>
    
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para><link linkend="FamilyFarmLevel">Family/Farm Level</link></para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para><link linkend="CommunityTownshipLevel">Community/Township Level</link></para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para><link linkend="CountyLevel">County Level</link></para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    
    <para>At each level, a different type of organization is required, different communication technologies are
        effective, and the audience for the information will be different. At the county and community/township level,
        we must also cover the glue which will be used to organize communities into manageable units within each
        county.
        Fortunately, as Missouri was laid out according to Public Land Survey<citebiblioid>895</citebiblioid>
        <glossterm>Quadrangle</glossterm>, <glossterm>Township</glossterm>, <glossterm>Section</glossterm> lines, we
        have natural units for that level of organization.</para>
    
    <para>It is recommended that each reader concentrate on the level of detail they are most interested in but also
        familiarize themselves with information at adjoining levels.
        Families, therefore, need to read the Family/Farm Level
        information thoroughly and be familiar with the Community/Township Level.
        County-level planners should read CountyLevel information thoroughly and become familiar with at least the
        Community/Township Level.
        People organizing neighborhood watch and township emergency services need to be familiar with all levels of
        information as the brunt of responding to any emergency is on your shoulders and you must coordinate both with
        individual families and county-level personnel.</para>
        
</chapter>
