<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" type="xml"?>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="Salt">
    <title>Salt</title>
    
    <indexterm zone="Salt">
        <primary>salt</primary>
    </indexterm>
    
    <para>Salt is a life-critical substance for human and livestock. It is required for food preservation, especially of meat, is one of the best antiseptics for cleaning meat-contaminated areas (such as butcher blocks), has medicinal value, and is an input into many small-farm industrial, or cottage-industry, or light industry processes (such as manufacture of lye or chlorine bleach).</para>
    
    <para>It is not, however, readily produced in Missouri in any form (there are some caves in Missouri from which salt might be mined but deposits are few and far between). Some plants concentrate certain salts (e.g. Walnut, potassium and dandelion, sodium) but these minerals must be replenished in the soil for this to occur. Even if we are producing our own food as well as fuel and other materials in Missouri, we will consume significant quantities of salt.</para>
    
    <para>The Sustainable Cedar County group has been ordering periodic semi-trailer loads of sea salt from Sea Agri (of 2000 pound pallets in 50 lb bags). Sea Agri provides a lab analysis of their salt which we have found to have sheep-safe levels of copper. Farms and groups in surrounding counties go in on this order and arrange pickup and distribution of bags or pallets from Stockton so that the salt supply ends up well-distributed. Other groups can do the same thing, ordering a semi-trailer in their area under a cooperative purchase and then distributing them by bag or pallet. Anyone with a truck and trailer could also buy directly from the distribution center.</para>
    
    <para>Following is the information for ordering:</para>
    
    <blockquote><literallayout>From: Robert
            Subject: SeaAgri
            Date: Tuesday, October 26, 2010, 3:18 PM</literallayout>
        
        <para>SeaAgri has made several improvements to our bagging and distribution
            effective 11/01/2010.</para>
        
        <para>New pricing has been established for both 2000 lb superbags and pallets of 50 lb bags. A new price schedule is attached along with a copy of our new label that is attached to each 50 lb bag.  These changes are relative to truckload orders of 22-24 tons only.</para>
        
        <para>SEA-90 is now provided in a properly weighed and labeled 5 mil vented, heat-sealed 50 lb bag. We guarantee 50-51 lbs in each bag and 40 bags per pallet.  Each pallet is made of oak and with product will weigh approx 2075 lbs and be fully shrink wrapped with a cardboard layer bottom and top for additional protection.</para>
        
        
        <para>Our primary warehouse and bagging operation is now located in Kansas City MO 64503.  All 2000 lb superbags and pallets of 50 lb bags will be shipped from this location. We will continue to provide superbag shipments from CA but not pallets of 50 lb bags.</para>
        
        <para>Our new warehouse facility is located within 80 miles of the geographical center of the United States and more centrally located to most of our customers.  As a result, freight charges should not change dramatically.  If you have trucking available, check your cost from Kansas City for truckload quantities.  We will continue to provide competitive freight pricing if required.  I will be happy to provide you with a quote upon request.</para>
        
        <para>Best Regards,</para>
        
        <para>Robert Cain
            President
            770-361-7003</para>
    </blockquote>
    
    <para>Jerry Diamond also mentions that the "cheapest way to get  it [bulk salt] is super totes from Cal-Mexico at $200 per ton; $4800.00 for 24 tons, one semi-load."</para>

</chapter>