<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" type="xml"?>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="TownshipSelfReliance">
    <title>Township Self-Reliance</title>
    
    <indexterm zone="TownshipSelfReliance">
        <primary>community/township</primary>
    </indexterm>
    
    <section><title>Overview</title>
    
    <para>This section is a place-holder for the WFNA material on PODs (Producer Organized Distribution System)
        and co-op formation (Joe Maxwell's, Russ Kramer's, and Ruell Chappel's presentations).
        Plus an index of local commerce groups and directories.</para>
    
    <para>Readers will also be interested in the <link linkend="LocalCurrency">Local Currency</link>
        article.</para>
    
    <para>The rest of this section is stray text in need of a home.</para>
       
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Checklist</title>
        
    <itemizedlist><title>10 point check list “B”</title>
        
        <listitem><para>Infrastructure inventory</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Production inventory</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Small Food Processing</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Team formation</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>Team roles</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Job formation</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Faith-based exchange</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Local-funding strategies</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>PR steps</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Transition Towns Wiki</title>
    
        <para><link xlink:href="http://www.transitiontowns.org/">Transition Towns</link>: a useful resource with proven
            “how-to’s” for getting started in your county.</para>
    

    
    <para>Although most people we've encountered here locally are not proponents of “peak oil” or
        “man-made climate change,” many do see real potential problems that necessitate the action prescribed
        in Transition Towns.
        Please go to the <link xlink:href="http://transitiontowns.org/TransitionNetwork/12Steps">12 Steps</link> link
        for the actual “how to do it” for a place to start.</para>
    
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Well Fed Dallas County (WFDC)</title>
    
    <para>Here is a resource to see how one immediate county has started their campaign.</para>
       
    <itemizedlist><title>Basic Progression (See Transition Town 12 Steps)</title>
        
        <listitem><para>Held (3) open meetings organized by one couple to find like minded individuals.
            The people were pooled from Homeschooling email groups. Look for any other “local” groups such
            as gardening clubs, 4H clubs and interested congregations.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>(3) couples were selected to Steering Committee (SC) positions, who expressed
            the most enthusiasm in seeing the project move forward and be successful.
            These were also the most faithful in attendance.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>A series of SC meetings were held to determine the specifics of the group;
            who we are, why we’re doing this, how we’re going to do it, etc.
            Here is a flyer we developed to hand out at all of our grassroots (GR) meetings to help convey
            the message;</para>
            
            <para>Well-Fed Dallas County</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>WFDC is a grassroots awareness and action campaign dedicated to food security, preparedness and economic
        prosperity for the people of Dallas County, Missouri.</para>
    
    <para>WFDC exists to support and encourage sustainability and preparedness through its neighbors, and to
        encourage and support cooperation between supermarkets, banks, entrepreneurs and county government
        to establish a local and sustainable food supply.</para>
    
    <para>WFDC works through bi-monthly grassroots meetings by bringing information and experts to address
        (3) key areas;</para>
    
    <para>FOOD: Gardening, Livestock, Processing , Production and Sales,</para>
    
    <para>PREPAREDNESS: Alternative Energy and Survival / Sustainable Living,</para>
    
    <para>And
        AWARENESS: Applicable News and Tracked Legislation</para>
    
    <para>WFDC believes that we can supply our own food; we can create jobs and a bustling economy through
        local agriculture.
        It is our goal to tap the resources and knowledge that exist right here in Dallas County,
        to produce better quality foods and a sustainable living regardless of circumstances beyond
        our control!
        Local agriculture and food production can guarantee economic sustainability and prosperity
        for generations to come!</para>
    
    <para>Come join us!</para>
    
    <para>Email: <link xlink:href="mailto:info@wfdc.us">info@wfdc.us</link></para>
    
    <para>Discussion Board: <link xlink:href="http://wfdc.us/discussion">http://wfdc.us/discussion</link></para>
    
    <para>Facebook: Well Fed Dallas County</para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>We developed an open Discussion Board for Dallas County citizen’s to share,
            make requests and generally just get involved;</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>Discussion Board:
        <link xlink:href="http://wfdc.us/discussion/">http://wfdc.us/discussion/</link></para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>We developed a basic GR meeting outline to keep interest and a more controlled environment.
            The thing we discovered immediately is that the excitement in the meetings leads to following rabbit
            trails and not much production.
            As noted in the flyer, there are 3 basic areas we cover and this is how it works;
            <orderedlist>
               <listitem><para>Awareness; 10-15 minutes. One SC member presents information as they’re capable.
                   Most people have no idea what is really going on.
                   We are not political in that we neither support nor attack any party.
                   We don’t care who’s in office or what party they’re with, only what they’re doing.</para></listitem>
                
            <listitem><para>Session 1; 30 minutes +/-. Either Food or Preparedness.</para></listitem>
                
            <listitem><para>Break; 10-15 minutes. The mind can only absorb what the behind can endure.
                We always encourage people to bring snacks, and one person from the SC is tasked with bringing
                coffee and associated stuff.</para></listitem>
                
            <listitem><para>Session 2; 30 minutes +/-. Either Food or Preparedness.</para></listitem>
                
            <listitem><para>Closing; 10-15 minutes.
                Here we issue challenges and requests.
                For example writing to the editors, bringing an immediate neighbor to the next meeting,
                etc.</para></listitem>
            </orderedlist></para></listitem>
            
        <listitem><para>Flexibility is key.
            There may be times when one key area may take up both sessions of a meeting.
            Some of the things we have done in past meetings are;
            Power Point presentations on winter survival and another on end of season garden soil
            preparation, Showed a 30 minute segment of “Meet the Farmer” featuring Joel Salatin and
            another clip from the “Future of Food.”
            We have done presentations on Agenda 21, Codex Alimentarius and the international use of
            food as a weapon.
            The meeting content possibilities are endless and people are amazed.</para></listitem>
            
        <listitem><para>Our last meeting of the year will be an heirloom/ open pollinated Seed Swap and
        Christmas get together. This will become a tradition for sure.</para></listitem>
            
        <listitem><para>Another beautiful thing about the GR meetings is that we don’t have to
            know everything.
            Point of fact is that we know very little, but then again, that is the point isn’t it.
            We don’t have to know everything, but we do have to know where to get answers.
            We bring in experts, whether in person or their work as public information.
            Verify your sources! Provide both sides of any issue and widely recognized as legitimate
            sources for anything you present.
            The SC chooses the topics and many times as interest is expressed at the GR meetings.
            Topics can be complimentary to growing seasons, animal husbandry or whatever.</para></listitem>
            
        <listitem><para>Meeting places;
            One of our local banks offers for free their meeting room and this is where we have the bulk
            of our GR meetings.
            In the future and as we branch out to each town, the local Lion’s Club’s offer their meeting
            rooms for a small fee. The SC meetings are rotated amongst SC member homes.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>Meeting Times and Dates;
            For the GR meetings, every other Thursday works best for us.
            Every week is too much for anybody responsible for content, and once a month is too little for
            those excited.
            No one day is magical in that everyone can attend, so just pick one and stick to it.
            Anything earlier than 7:00 is too early for anyone who has to drive for any distance, and
            staying until 8:30 – 9:00 is really not too late for anyone really interested.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>The SC meetings are really fun. We always meet over a really good meal and the
            ladies have fun doing it.
            It’s nice to have one person chair the meeting, but authority should never be an issue.
            We’re all in this together and everyone should have equal say and influence.
            These meetings are held every other week between the GR meetings.
            Here we discuss the content of the following GR meeting, special events, and generally, typical
            business stuff.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>Volunteers have not been a problem. One person started a Facebook page for us.
            Another offered graphics services. The message breeds enthusiasm.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>WFDC has been interviewed by one local paper (yet to be published), and has
            had one meeting reported on by another paper. The individual writing for us volunteered
            after attending the same meeting.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>About Well Fed Dallas County; (As determined by the SC):</para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>This information is peculiar to WFDC.
        Every individual county should work as they decide what is appropriate for their area.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>The endgame of our group is to work ourselves out of a job!
            The vision shared by the SC is one in which the things we are sharing become second nature and a way of
            life for the citizens of Dallas County.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>We have decided that we are autonomous in that we are directly connected to no other
            group or organization.
            This allows us to accept or reject anything as it pertains to Dallas County.
            We are certainly supportive of WFNA.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>We are not interested in tax exempt status or any other direct or indirect interaction
            with the Federal Government especially considering the restrictions and rules that inevitably go
            with it.
            That being said, we are not for profit nor do we seek donations of any kind except that of personal
            resources volunteered as needed to accomplish our goals.</para></listitem>
        
        </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>The Future of WFDC; (As being worked out by the SC)</para>
    
    <para>The SC has determined that immediately we will be going to every town in Dallas County with the
        GR meetings.
        One town at a time to make people aware and start them off on their own campaigns.
        It’s the opinion of the SC that once the foundation is laid all over the county, then the powers
        that be will have no choice but to fall in line.</para>
    
    <para>The SC will be working on markets for local products.
        The growers need incentive to grow, the entrepreneurs need incentive to produce and the
        banks need incentive to finance.
        This will require the help of our supermarkets, retailers and local government</para>
    
    </section>    
        
    <section><title>BuyLocalDirectory</title>
        
        <para>Where to buy and sell local goods, especially farm products.</para>
        
        <section><title>Directories</title>
        
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><link xlink:href="http://localharvest.org/">LocalHarvest</link></term>
                <listitem><para>A national directory of local farms and locally available
                farm goods. Local farms and groups (such as farmers' markets) can obtain accounts, post
                information, maintain a calendar of events, and sell goods, either through the Local
                Harvest Catalog or through their own website.
                Customers can search their area for products, farms, and events by zip code.</para></listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
            
    </section>
        
        <section><title>Lawrence County (or nearby) Markets and Cooperatives</title>
        
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Mount Vernon Farmers' Market</term>
                <listitem><para>Mount Vernon, MO. Saturdays in season on the town square.
                    Producers' Market organized under the Mount Vernon Chamber of Commerce.
                    Farm inspection required. Season begins with Founders' Day festival and ends
                    with Apple Butter Making Days.</para></listitem>
            </varlistentry>
                           
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Aurora Farmers' Market</term>
                <listitem><para>Aurora, MO. There are actually two farmers' markets operating in
                    Aurora, one of which, on the east side of the park Wednesdays and Saturdays,
                    is a producer's market.</para></listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Webb City Farmers' Market</term>
                <listitem><para>In Jaspar County, but accepts Lawrence County Vendors.
                    It is an outdoor market with a shelter for vendors.
                    An excellent, well-run market which tries to balance between producers
                    and value-added (e.g. jellies, crafts).
                    Farm inspection required.
                    High traffic in season. Market runs Tuesday, Friday, and Saturday.</para></listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Sarcoxie Farmers' Market</term>
                <listitem><para>An informal market run on Saturdays on the town square in season.</para></listitem>
            </varlistentry> 
        </variablelist>
        </section>
    </section>
    
    <section><title>RebuildingMainStreet</title>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>Vulnerability Audit</para></listitem>
        
            <listitem><para>Energy Descent Planning</para></listitem>
        
            <listitem><para>Grocery store revival</para></listitem>
        
            <listitem><para>11/27 LOCAL BREAD BAKERY
            <link xlink:href="http://www.hillbillyhousewife.com/category/recipes/bread/breadmachine">http://www.hillbillyhousewife.com/category/recipes/bread/breadmachine</link></para></listitem>        

            <listitem><para>Strategic Marketing</para></listitem>
        
            <listitem><para>Bio fuels</para></listitem>
        
            <listitem><para>Church &amp; Civic leaders</para></listitem>
        
            <listitem><para>Sheriff and safe passes</para></listitem>
            
        </itemizedlist>
        
    </section>
        
    <section><title>GoulburnWoolScour</title>
        
        <para><link xlink:href="http://www.gwsr.com.au/index.htm">http://www.gwsr.com.au/index.htm</link></para>
                
        <para>The web site of a wool scouring plant in Australia that has a sophisticated process for cleaning
            wool and minimizing environmental impact, including co-generation (lanolin, irrigation water,
            dirt for erosion repair in pastures, heat exchangers in scour water) and grey-water usage.</para>
                
        <para>There is no reason that much of their process could not be duplicated on a much smaller scale
            for wool processing in Missouri.
            We have many people who raise sheep in Missouri, the land is well-suited to it, but many raise
            wool-less breeds ("hair sheep") like the Katadin, or simply discard the wool because there is
            no nearby processing.
            It is too expensive to send the wool to South America and back.</para>

    </section>
        
        <section><title>PioneerThinkingNaturalDyes</title>
            
                <para>“Making Natural Dyes From Plants.” Pioneer Thinking, December 12, 2009.
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.pioneerthinking.com/naturaldyes.html">http://www.pioneerthinking.com/naturaldyes.html</link>.</para>
                
                <para>This is an article covering the very basics of using plant dyes with vinegar or salt fixatives
                    with a list of plants and the colors obtained.</para>
                
                <para>There is no way to determine when the article was written.
                    The data above is simply when I last accessed the page.</para>
        </section>
</chapter>
