<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" type="xml"?>

<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="CastleDefenseSystem">
    <title>Castle Defense System</title>
    
    <indexterm zone="CastleDefenseSystem">
        <primary>disaster preparation</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm zone="CastleDefenseSystem">
        <primary>emergency management</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm zone="CastleDefenseSystem">
        <primary>leadership/planning</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm zone="CastleDefenseSystem">
        <primary>march</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm zone="CastleDefenseSystem">
        <primary>neighborhood watch</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm zone="CastleDefenseSystem">
        <primary>resilient communication</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm zone="CastleDefenseSystem">
        <primary>riding</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm zone="CastleDefenseSystem">
        <primary>security and defense</primary>
        <secondary>castle defense</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm zone="CastleDefenseSystem">
        <primary>transportation</primary>
    </indexterm>
    
    <para>A working "castle defense system" such as that which evolved around Medieval keeps and monasteries,
        is more than a military structure. It was organized for local commerce, communication, emergency management,
        and crime control in addition to defense. It was connected into a wider system of roads, posts, and circuit
        courts.
        We will be working with an idealized system adapted for modern community-level planning, but the principles
        are similar to what has worked for millennia.</para>
    
    <para>The castle system developed in a time of trouble and tribulation to allow areas of the countryside to
        pull together and respond to emergencies with the greatest efficiency possible.
        In a time where local budgets and economies are stressed, police and sheriff's departments are cutting back on
        patrols, and fuel prices are unstable, duplicating a time-tested and efficient system is worthwhile.</para>
    
    <para>In this system, the countryside is divided into manageable chunks based on the area which can be reasonably
        covered by marching infantry or horseman within one day.
        A "March" is defined as the area which can be reasonably patrolled on foot over the course of a day, and a
        'Riding' as the area which can be patrolled on horseback over the same day.
        These are the areas in which communication, commerce, and response to developing situations can be managed in
        the absence of long range radio, telephone, and motorized transport.
        It should be noted that even when vehicles and fuel are available, the medieval divisions still make sense
        as roads, conditions, or simply funds may act to limit patrol areas in the same manner.</para>
    
    <para>An infantry unit can march between 10 and 20 miles in one day, or 5-10 miles one way from a central base
        with some pack and baggage in favorable terrain.
        Light patrols returning to prepared meals and bedding push the top of this envelope.
        A cavalry unit can move 15-25 miles in one day or 8 to 12 miles round trip. Horse scouts with light
        equipment and no rolling stock can push 20-40 miles between dawn and dusk in favorable terrain.
        For our purposes, we will use a 6 mile radius for foot patrols and a 12 mile radius for horse patrols.
        These are approximate but reasonable values which are particularly convenient in Missouri, as will
        be discussed.
        The limits of horse patrols are a decent approximation for what can be accomplished with motorized
        vehicles in bad conditions and they also describe the limits of some mobile two-way radio technology
        for use in coordinating patrols.</para>
    
    <figure>
        <title>March and Riding Illustrated</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/marchridingillus.png" width="6in"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject><phrase>A diagram of how CastleDefense is organized into Marches and Ridings.</phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    
    <para>Typically, each military district has one or more small strongholds which operate as a center of
        communications, fortress, and emergency shelter in time of need.
        'Fortress' is something which is not often needed these days as even in time of war, they cannot
        withstand modern weaponry, but the other functions of a central keep, fort, or monastery are still
        applicable.
        In the past, these central points naturally became a focus of trade and commerce.</para>
    
    <para>A warning system of bells, beacons, or mounted heralds notified the populace of impending emergency,
        at which point the local militia would report to the keep and the populace, if necessary, would flee
        to it.
        A network of foot and horse patrols would keep the central location apprised of the developing
        situation.
        The keep was prepared in advance to have stores of food and fodder, arms and equipment, as well as
        shelter for citizens and animals.
        Most modern emergency response plans provide <emphasis>no</emphasis> thought whatsoever for saving
        livestock during a civil shutdown or evacuation.
        For those living in the medieval period, giving thought to such things was a matter of daily life
        (or death).</para>
    
    <section><title>The Public Land Survey System (PLSS) and Castle Defense</title>
    
        <figure>
            <title>March and Riding in the Public Land Survey System Diagram</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/plsmarchriding.png" width="6in"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject><phrase>A diagram of how marches and ridings are mapped to the Public Land Survey
                    System (PLSS) units.</phrase></textobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    
    <para>Under the Missouri Public Land Survey system, land was surveyed out from a longitude and latitude
        "range lines" into <glossterm>townships</glossterm> of six miles square.
        Each township was divided into 36 one mile square <glossterm>Sections</glossterm>.
        A group of four townships by four (16 total) is a <glossterm>Quadrangle</glossterm>.
        In Lawrence County and other areas of Missouri, Farm Roads are numbered according to section lines
        and form a grid on one mile markers (e.g. FR 1060 is one mile from and runs parallel to FR 1050).
        Corrections for survey error and the Earth's curvature are made at township boundaries, which is
        why you will find sudden jags in the roads at those points.</para>
    
    <para>This system, as shown in the diagram, is readily adapted to Castle Defense principles.
        A group of four townships is considered to be a March and a Quadrangle is considered to be a Riding.
        This means that (at least) every four townships should have one central rally point and shelter capable
        of putting out emergency personnel on foot (if necessary) and every Quadrangle should have a significant
        outpost capable of putting out mounted or mechanized personnel in any emergency.
        These figures must be adapted to the needs of specific terrain and conditions.</para>
    
    <para>Within this system, Neighborhood Watches are organized (see <link
        linkend="RuralWatchArea">RuralWatchArea</link>).
        Each watch is set up to report to a Township-level Watch Coordinator by phone, radio or, if necessary,
        by horse or runner (this is why distances are critically important).
        Each Neighborhood Watch is responsible for no more than 3 miles by 3 miles (a quarter of a township)
        and may be significantly less in settled areas.
        Patrols are organized and referred to on section lines.
        For ease of use, when we refer to a Rural Watch, we will be talking about a 3 mile square area (9 sections).
        Occasionally, we will need to talk about watches which do not conform to this norm.</para>
    
    <para>Within each watch, the Castle Defense is mirrored on a smaller level.
        There is a central house or houses (Watch HQ) which are connected, in whatever fashion, to the emergency
        communications structure and which emergency personnel know to check at for local information.
        Each family in the neighborhood is able to communicate with the Watch HQ and knows to go there for news.
        In time of emergency, the Watch HQ is the rally point for volunteers on their way up the chain to Township
        HQ so they can be directed from the March HQ on where they are needed.</para>
    
    <para>Each Watch also arranges so that people in the neighborhood can group together when needed,
        especially to put children, invalids, and elderly in a central location to free up volunteers
        for emergency response. At each level, Watch HQ, Township HQ, and March HQ, it is important to
        be able to quickly set up a field kitchen and aid station so that injured, refugees, and returning
        volunteers can get a meal and comfort.</para>
    
    <para>The Riding HQ should be set up to be able to deal with an influx of volunteers, injured, and
        refugees from its entire Quadrangle (16 townships).
        It also needs to be able to operate as a temporary headquarters for County-level personnel who may be
        moving from location to location to manage a developing emergency.
        The Riding needs to have state-to-regional communications abilities, post-dispatch (e.g., by horse
        courier) between Ridings, and the ability to quickly get volunteers and emergency personnel to the
        townships where they are needed.
        Both the Riding and March HQs need to have a ready-to-use map room where up-to-date information on the
        terrain, situation, and capabilities can be quickly spread out and worked with.
        Maps must have township and section boundaries to make coordination easier.
        These are available from the County Assessor's office.</para>
    
    <para>At at least the Neighborhood Watch level, the headquarters will simply be one of the local homes.
        At the Township, March, and Riding levels, it is more likely that a church, school, fire hall or
        other facility will be available.
        In many cases, the choice will be dominated by road access and line-of-site for communications.</para>
    
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Urban Centers</title>
    
    <para>Obviously urban centers are a wrinkle in this system.
        Wherever possible, an available urban center should be used as the March or Riding HQ with a backup
        facility outside the urban area in case of a need to evacuate the urban center.
        In many cases, an urban center will be a Riding of its own and the Ridings around it will be
        correspondingly smaller.
        As we go forward, we will compile Missouri maps with these issues resolved.</para>
    
    </section>
</section>
