<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" type="xml"?>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="CommunityTownshipLevel">
    <title>Community/Township Level</title>
    
    <indexterm zone="CommunityTownshipLevel">
        <primary>disaster preparation</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm zone="CommunityTownshipLevel">
        <primary>emergency management</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm zone="CommunityTownshipLevel">
        <primary>township/community</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm zone="CommunityTownshipLevel">
        <primary>leadership/planning</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm zone="CommunityTownshipLevel">
        <primary>economic/community restoration</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm zone="CommunityTownshipLevel">
        <primary>resilient communications</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm zone="CommunityTownshipLevel">
        <primary>security and defense</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm zone="CommunityTownshipLevel">
        <primary>transportation</primary>
    </indexterm>
    
    <figure>
        <title>Community/Township Level</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/communitytownshiplevel.png" scalefit="1"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    
    <section><title>Overview</title>
    
    <para>The community and township level of detail is the heart of the Handbook.
        It is where every effort is brought together, from <link
            linkend="FarmRestoration">FarmRestoration</link> to <link
                linkend="CountyLevelDisasterPreparation">CountyLevelDisasterPreparation</link>.
        The Township level is the smallest level of self-government and the because of short
        distances involved; it is the level of communication and decision making most likely to
        be able to act decisively in an emergency.
        In many cases, this action must be taken autonomously, without coordination from County-level
        leadership.
        This means that it is crucial for emergency response plans to be coordinated between county
        and township level <emphasis>before</emphasis> disaster strikes and that local people must exist who are
        considered to have the authority to act.</para>
    
    <para>Community-level planning is best accomplished using the principles of
        <link linkend="CastleDefense">CastleDefense</link>: local safe areas with surrounding zones
        establishing communications, emergency response, and community defense based on distances
        easily handled by walking or riding.
        In the Dark Ages, a time of great turmoil in Europe, local manors and monasteries were organized
        in this manner and often organized into military districts referred to as Marches and Ridings.
        Using this system of organization ensures that low-tech methods are available for communications
        when hi-tech methods are for some reason not available.</para>
    
    <para>The <glossterm>Public Land Survey System</glossterm> (PLSS) used when Missouri
        was first surveyed is already well laid out for community-level planning and emergency response.
        Each <glossterm>Township</glossterm> is a 6 mile square of 36 1-mile sections.
        This size was selected because anyone in the township can walk into the center, do business,
        and walk back out within the course of a day.
        Someone can readily walk from one township to the next for the purposes of a farmers' market
        or other commerce.
        A <glossterm>Quadrangle</glossterm>, a square consisting of four townships-by-four, is an area
        which can be readily covered by horseback or horse-drawn conveyances when and if needed.
        These squares are already surveyed and numbered for use in community planning.
        Horse or mechanized post can connect Ridings together when necessary and the Riding Headquarters
        can function as temporary County Command Posts as County officials circulate to deal with an ongoing
        crisis.</para>
    
    <note><info><author><personname><firstname>Eric</firstname><surname>Vought</surname></personname></author>
        <title>Township Term Confusion</title></info>
        
        <para>It should be noted that Missouri has several conflicting and layered definitions of
        <glossterm>Township</glossterm>.
        We are talking about the original survey lines here, not political boundaries.---Eric Vought</para>
        </note>
    
    <figure>
        <title>Watch Area Communications Diagram</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/WatchHierarchyandComm.png" width="6in"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    
    <para>This diagram shows what such a hierarchy might look like and the
        <link linkend="TwoWayCommunications">TwoWayCommunications</link> which might be usable at each level.
        Exactly which communications technologies are used in each area depends on terrain and line-of-sight,
        on roads, foot/horse paths and fordings, on existing practice, on the nature of an emergency, and on
        the availability of qualified volunteers.
        Telephone, the cell network, and texting are options at all levels when they are functioning.</para>
    
    <para>The basic level of organization at this level is the
        <link linkend="NeighborhoodWatch">Neighborhood Watch</link>.
        Urban Neighborhood Watch policies and procedures are already fairly well described.
        Here we concentrate on developing effective strategies for
        <link linkend="RuralWatchArea">Rural Watch Areas</link>.</para>
    
    <sidebar>
        <info><author><personname><firstname>Jerry</firstname><surname>Diamond</surname></personname></author>
            <title>Discussion</title></info>
        
        <para>FYI , just to start putting some numbers on "paper" -- in an area of 100 mile radius there will
            be 31,400 square miles.
            Pi, which is 3.14 times radius squared = 3.14 x 100 x 100= 31,400 sq.mi.</para>
        
        <para>A Township is 36 sq mi, so 31,400 divided by 36 = 872 townships.
            Many of those will have a good farm; how many?
            We need to find, identify and keep in touch with those farmers, and develop good farms in the
            townships which do not have one.
            Another option is to make sure that there is some viable industry which can allow that township
            to support itself via barter, etc.</para>
        
        <para>Protection of those farms, as a core part of Castle Defense // Guardener Systems will be paramount.
            I am going to proceed , as to the Pyramid Defense System I am working on, to have each of those
            Farm / Castles protected.
            I had always wondered what kind of grid would be necessary to protect the entire region,
            and since each Township Farm / Castle needs to be secure, that answers the question as to how many
            systems might be needed.</para>
        
        <para>We could begin by placing one per county, then one per March, then one per township...</para>
        
        <para>A Riding, 16 Townships, or 4 Marches,   is close to the size of each county.</para>
        
        <para>We are then talking about approximately 16 +/- farms per county, which should be an excellent
            basis for protection, trade, redundancy, seed saving, etc. within that local vicinity.</para>
        
        <para>Dividing the total projected  31,400 sq mi by 16 Townships of 36 sq mi, and again by 16
            Townships per county, that gives us 55 counties give or take.</para>
        
        <para>Stated differently, 36 sq mi per TS x 16 TS per Riding, or County, = 576 sq mi per Riding, or
            County.
            Divide the "BIG CIRCLE" ** by 576, and you have 55 Ridings/Counties.</para>
        
        <para>This number of 576  is fairly accurate, on the average, for smaller counties, as Cedar County is
            499 sq mi, and Lawrence is 613 sm, Dade is 506 sm.
            There are bigger counties, Vernon at 837, Howell at 928, while, go figure!!!;
            "Texas County, the largest of Missouri’s 114 counties, comprises 1,179 square miles of Ozark Highland.
            With the same name as the second largest of the fifty U.S. states, larger than the smallest State
            (Rhode Island 1,045 square miles), in terms of total land area."</para>
        
        <para>These figures are just a place to start to give us an idea of what kind of level of magnitude we are
            speaking of.
            Another way to look at it is that Missouri is 70,000 sq mi.
            Looking at the map, it looks like the area we are talking about would equal about half of the area of
            Missouri.
            Again, some figures to get us somewhere in the ballpark.</para>
        
        <para>---Jerry Diamond</para>
        
    </sidebar>
    </section>
    
    <xi:include href="castledefensesystem.xml"/>
    
</chapter>