<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" type="xml"?>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="DisasterPreparationGoal">
    <title>Disaster Preparation</title>
    
    <indexterm zone="DisasterPreparationGoal">
        <primary>disaster preparation</primary>
    </indexterm>
    
    <para>Restoration of our communities makes our economy healthier, avoids many emergencies which might otherwise
        be caused by short or long term economic collapse, and prepares people to weather short-term calamities.
        No community can produce every single tool, resource, or material it needs, however.
        Even a healthy, robust community will have trouble handling major calamities and long-term disruption of 
        supply lines without specific emergency planning. 
        Such a disruption could be a natural occurrence or man-made, it could involve earthquakes, disease, warfare, monetary devaluation or embargo.</para>
    
    <section><title>What could trigger a long emergency?</title>
    
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>A natural disaster – The giant volcano under Yellowstone Park could erupt. Giant earthquakes along the Mississippi valley or California could split the earth. Super storms could devastate coastal cities and the ports that bring in food and fuel.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>Military action. If nuclear weapons were used against Iran the world could be plunged into a world war with nuclear and biological weapons. A nuclear device exploded in the space above the USA could disrupt the entire electrical and communication system and put the nation in total darkness. Even a conventional war can interrupt shipping, take away a significant portion of the workforce for military service, or cause rationing of resources.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Monetary devaluation or foreign trade policies could lead to US citizens not being able to purchase imported products. The current US depression could continue or get worse, leading to either hyperinflation (worthless money) or capital starvation (too little money). Growing federal debt could lead to the dollar being devalued against other currencies. Foreign trade partners could embargo the US (or simply stop lending money) for political reasons.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Other oil extracting nations could shut off our fuel imports like OPEC did in 1973. This could shut down the transportation of food and other life essentials.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Corporations that control the production and distribution of oil, coal, electricity, water and food could create an artificial shortage and inflate the prices like Enron did for the State of California and British Petroleum (BP) that is responsible for the oil that is gushing into the Gulf of Mexico</para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    
    <para>Most emergency planning is focused on localized emergencies like fires, ice storms, earthquakes, floods, but most plans assume that the basic infrastructure will still be in place -- communication network, electrical grid and fuel supply. There are few backup plans for major disasters that shut down the whole system for an extended period. We really do not know what might cause the next major emergency of this type, but, historically, we know that major upheavals, from the "Year Without a Summer" to World Wars, do occur from time to time. Our ancestors survived many of them, and, with some care, we can too.</para>
    
    <para>It should be noted that we are not talking about "extinction events" or "world-ending catastrophes". By definition, no planning will help those circumstances. Nor is it even realistic to plan, beyond a certain point, for catastrophic events where we, ourselves, are at ground zero. Instead, we plan for regional disasters or catastrophic events which disrupt everything around us, where a community survives the initial circumstances relatively intact and needs to move forward from there. We will discuss this in depth in the next section.</para>
    
    <note><title>Principle</title>
        <para>We do not plan for the asteroid falling on our own town but for the asteroid falling several towns
        over.</para>
    </note>
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Specific Planning Scenarios</title>
    
    <para>It is helpful to have specific scenarios in mind to focus planning and to test plans against.
        What level of disaster can we plan for and for how long? For the most part, it does not matter at this point what the specific emergency might be: loss of outside resources, destruction of local crops, loss of national communication and disruption of government will be similar in a wide variety of circumstances. More specific scenarios can be considered down the road to fine-tune plans and make them more flexible in specific circumstances.</para>
    
    <para>As such, the following yardstick is proposed:</para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>a 75% reduction in availability of imported goods</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>a resultant price increase in domestic and remaining imported goods</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>a duration of 18 months, tapering off thereafter</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>Loss of up to 50% of domestic crops in the first year</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>The percentage reductions are somewhat arbitrary, although supported by historical events. Very few events completely eliminate outside commerce for any significant length of time. Goods do get through, even if their price becomes exceedingly high ("Black Market"). The time frame is chosen to reflect the time taken to restore normal crop cycles. Disasters do not just destroy crops but also perennial plants, mature vines and trees, seed stock. Shortages cause farmers and mouths to compete for the same grain. Orchards must be cleaned up and pruned after storms. It generally takes more than one complete crop cycle to either restore normalcy or begin new kinds of production.</para>
    
    <para>If a community loses 100% of its local production due to disaster, it generally cannot be expected to survive without help from less affected communities. In that case, disaster mitigation is a question of surviving long enough for that help to arrive and start being effective. A 50% loss of production is itself a severe planning challenge in a situation where outside imports have also been degraded. If local losses happen to be less than this, then your community is one of the "less affected" which can perhaps begin helping its neighbors to survive.</para>
    
    <para>This scenario does not make specific statements on <emphasis>which</emphasis> resources will be degraded. A 75% loss of imports could mean that certain product categories are wiped out entirely and others are nearly unaffected. A Mid-East war and embargo, for instance, might still allow unrestricted imports from South America, including some petroleum products.  Mitigation plans should take this into account, state their specific assumptions, and focus on adaptability in using one resource to cover the loss of another.</para>
    
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Who will help us survive a major emergency?</title>
    
    <para>The Federal Government and the international corporations that control the governments in most nations cannot be trusted to do anything to protect us from a long energy and food emergency. The government failed completely to respond to hurricane Katrina even though it was predicted to strike the city at least 3 days in advance. New Orleans and the Gulf Coast are still trying to recover from this disaster.</para>
    
    <para>In general, a top-down national structure is not helpful for responding to major emergencies. We have local government in the US because it is not possible for a centralized government to understand and plan for the unique needs of each community. By definition, a major emergency is one in which even the normal rules do not apply and therefore, it is impossible for a central system to understand what resources are needed where. In addition, it is morally reprehensible for the central government to be responsible for making decisions when critical resources cannot go far enough: essentially deciding who lives and who dies.</para>
    
    <para>When hurricane Floyd struck North Carolina in 1999, the relief organizations, fueled by massive private donations, had enough water, supplies, and volunteers to help people. What they did not have was adequate information on what was needed and the logistical tracking to know what was available to them. When even local emergency personnel on site cannot determine these things, an outside structure second-guessing their decisions is no help. It should also be noted that communities across the Carolinas were disrupted by the storm even though they were not directly struck. A flood of refugees from the Outer Banks closed schools in Raleigh, NC for weeks.</para>
    
    <para>The massive “national security system” that takes over 50% of our national budget did not protect us on
        September 11, 2001.
        It is not prepared to protect us from other long emergencies and the collapse of the infrastructure.
        The nation electrical power grid is a fragile system where whole sections can collapse from pressure at a
        single point (as evidenced by the <link
            xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northeast_Blackout_of_2003">Northeast Blackout of 2003</link>) .
        Without electricity, fuel for transportation could not be pumped into transport trucks.
        Without electricity, banks would no longer be able to provide money for business transactions.
        Food imported from other nations and states would stop flowing.
        Grocery stores would be out of food in less than three days and within two weeks we would begin to have famine conditions.
        The last of the national emergency food supply was sold off in 2009 <annotation><para>CitationNeeded</para></annotation>.
        The nation has no food grain reserves in storage—zero, zilch, nothing.</para>
    
    <para>The government may impose marshal law to control people, but this will not provide people with food, water and fuel. Many state national guard units have been deployed overseas, and, as evidenced by Hurricane Katrina (2005), are not in position to help in local emergencies. Communities must have plans in place to respond locally, provide emergency supplies, and <emphasis>help neighboring communities</emphasis>.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Examples of unexpected emergencies</title>
    
    <para>When the Soviet Union collapsed there was great disruption and suffering.
        The island of Cuba had its petroleum supply line cut off from the USSR and no other nations were
        willing to help them.
        They were forced to come up with alternatives in food production, transportation, utilities and
        other essential services.
        [They suffered famine conditions for almost 4 years until the people
        <link xlink:href="http://www.yidio.com/power-community-how-cuba-survived-peak-oil/id/3523075460"></link> through cooperation and ingenuity managed to create alternative systems.
        Now they are healthier than before.]</para>
    
    <para>Springfield, Missouri experienced an ice storm that cut off electricity to large populations for 10 days or more and they saw how quickly the food disappeared from the grocery stores, their homes became cold, and they were beginning to go hungry.</para>
    
    </section>
    
    <section><title>The purpose of governments – to provide services for the community.</title>
    
    <para>Local and state governments have been created specifically to provide needed services, resources and security for the citizens of the community. These include protection from criminals that threaten our life and property (police &amp; courts). Protect from fires – (fire departments) Protection from weather and natural disasters (weather department – disaster relief – national guard) Safe water supply (city water departments) Transportation infrastructure – public roads and highways – land given for railroads – air traffic control systems Food production – agriculture agency with seed development &amp; education. Food security &amp; inspection. Family services for children, mothers, etc. Emergency shelters. In fact all the parts of local governments are responsible to the people for maintaining services, security and resources for the people.</para>
    
    <para>Over-dependency on these leads to fragile communities which cannot survive disruptions. Over-dependence is characterized by the following conditions:</para>
    
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>More services are procured and more promises made (e.g. police/fire retirement plans) than can be paid in lean times. Either the locality borrows money, depend on boom tax revenues which will not be present in economic downturn, or simply promise more than can be fulfilled in order to secure votes. This leads to the probability that services will be suddenly cut when money runs out.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Neighborhoods and families do not have stores, supplies, or skills locally where they are needed. Citizens do not participate in emergency services but rather treat them as something they are simply entitled to be provided. When an emergency disrupts services, especially transportation and communications, people cannot help themselves let alone others around them. This causes panic and panic is deadly in a disaster.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>People do not develop the relationships and communications within their neighborhoods and with local emergency personnel to be able to work as a team in time of disaster. A high-casualty event such as a tornado enough wounded to rapidly overwhelm local emergency services and personnel. Emergency services require citizens with no or minor injuries to help those who are worse off, but if citizens do not have the training necessary to assist and have not developed the team skills necessary to work with those more trained, then they may actually make things worse. Assigning four people to a task does not make them a team. Team skills and relationships need to be developed before disaster strikes. Similarly, having two-way radios in a disaster without knowing how to use them, who will be listening, what channels to use, and what protocols are required to use shared effectively is worse-than-useless. These are not things which can be decided and imposed by government--- they must be worked out in the communities which will be affected.</para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    
    <para>We the people must demand that government workers and elected officials do the job they have been employed to do. That means planning for lean times as well as good. It means staying within a budget for services which can be maintained throughout the economic cycle. If officials cannot do that then they must be replaced. But we must also demand from ourselves that we do not expect something for nothing, we consider the costs of handouts we are offered, and we expect to work with emergency professionals and trained volunteers at the local level, to develop required relationships, build team skills, and obtain the training needed to work within our own neighborhoods when necessary.</para>
    
    <para>Many people argue that armed citizenry maximizes the chance that a "good guy" will be present when an incident occurs and will reduce the chance that an incident results in mass murder of defenseless civilians. However, it is hypocritical to not extend the same reasoning to the carrying of first aid supplies and the provisioning of our neighborhoods, homes, vehicles, and businesses with emergency stores.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section><title>The Proposed Action Plan</title>
    
    <para>Local citizens need to organize a cooperative system to create a Vulnerability Assessment and an Emergency Backup plan of action. Local government can and should be part of this plan, but much of the energy and input must come from the individual citizens who will be on the hook to implement the plan in time of need.</para>
    
    <para>The proposal has two parts: 1) a vulnerability assessment for each town or city and
        2) a set of proposals for creating alternative back up supply systems for electricity, fuel, transportation, food and water. These back up systems should be designed to take effect within 3 days after a national or local emergency and should be designed to last for at least six months.</para>
    
    <para>These plans should not depend on Federal Government funding and should be locally/privately funded as much as possible and make use of volunteers. Every household should be urged to develop their personal vulnerability assessment and their plan for back up food, water, transportation, fuel and communication.</para>
    
    <para>Emergency stores must be distributed throughout the community whenever possible. This maximizes the chance that they will be close to where they are needed when transportation is disrupted and that centralized stores cannot be wiped out by the same event which causes the disaster. Families and neighborhoods will be responsible for allocating stores locally and for transporting a portion up to the next level of community for helping others and they must be prepared to do this without outside direction when required. What coordination occurs should happen within and on top of the <link linkend="RuralWatchArea">RuralWatchArea</link> structure.</para>
    
    <para>Existing organizations, such as the American Red Cross, Lutheran World Relief, the Salvation Army, ARES, the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, and so forth, already exist to organize much of this effort at the community level and create centralized emergency communications/shelters/aid stations. The structure to organize this at the neighborhood level to fill gaps in and coordinate with these volunteer efforts mostly does not exist. Most people would not know where to go for help, would not know where to go to offer help, do not have basic required skills, and do not have the required emergency supplies to even survive until help arrives.</para>
    
    <para>This needs to be fixed immediately.</para>
    
    <para>Without waiting for the government.</para>
    
    <para>We the people, without waiting for the government, need to re-localize our total economy – food, energy and money, and wean ourselves from dependence upon energy and food imported by international corporations from other nations. This makes us very vulnerable and insecure. The military “national security system” does nothing to provide security for our food, energy and economy (jobs).</para>
    
    <para>This is what Well-Fed Neighbor movement is attempting to do.</para>
    
    <para>Preparation needed</para>
    
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>Create a power point to illustrate how 95% food and 70% of oil is imported from other
            nations and states.</para>
            <orderedlist>
            <listitem><para>Fruit labels showing production location</para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>Graph showing percentage from sources</para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>Energy imports from sources</para></listitem>

            </orderedlist>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>Create illustrations what will happen if the supply lines break down.</para>
        <orderedlist>    
            <listitem><para>Possible causes of a long term emergency</para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>b. Systems that would break down</para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>Effect in the community</para></listitem>
        </orderedlist></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>Create a vulnerability assessment outline for towns and cities.</para>
        <orderedlist>    
            <listitem><para>Water supply</para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>Electrical source</para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>Gas &amp; oil supply chain</para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>Food resources</para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>Basic medical supplies</para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>Communications and political continuity</para></listitem>
        </orderedlist></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>Create a plan of action for towns &amp; cities to cope with a long term emergency without Federal government.</para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>
        
        </section>
</chapter>
