<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" type="xml"?>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="FoodOverview">
    <title>Overview</title>
    
    <indexterm zone="FoodOverview">
        <primary>food</primary>
    </indexterm>
    
    <para>Something to think about:</para>
    
    <para>Salt is a real commodity. It is every bit as real as gold. The difference is that gold will not preserve food, make it taste better, heal disease, or fertilize your crops, garden, orchard, or vineyard. You can't eat gold as many people have historically found out who hoarded it, thinking it was the end-all hedge against hard times. If that is all you have when hard times hit, you are out of luck, and scripture says it will thrown out into the street. In Eze 7:19:</para>
    
    <blockquote>
        <para>They shall cast their silver in the streets, and their gold shall be removed: their silver and their gold shall not be able to deliver them in the day of the wrath of the LORD: they shall not satisfy their souls, neither fill their bowels: because it is the stumbling block of their iniquity.</para>
    </blockquote>
    
    <section><title>Meat On the Hoof and Crops In the Ground</title>
    
    <para>This is where we need to be heading if we want to consider ourselves wealthy.  We need to have food and it needs to be food that is growing.  The best form of food preservation is meat on the hoof and crops in the ground.  Another experience my son and I had, way back when we were in Denver, happened in a restaurant which “counter-culture” types often frequented; you know, you’d have radicals and patriots and all kinds of different people.  This one gentleman was sitting up at the counter and we were sitting at a booth.  He was talking to somebody about his investments and buying stock in DIA (Denver International Airport).  I made a comment out loud to him while they were talking.  Later I made another comment out loud, and so a while later, after his friend left, he came and sat down at the booth with us and told us about how you could get a ten percent discount on Canadian gold maple leaves if you drove to Canada and bought a quarter of a million dollars at a time.  And I said, “Ian, what are we waiting for, let’s go.”</para>
    
    </section>
    <section><title>The Garden Was Worth More Than The Gold</title>
    
    <para>He did recognize, however, that while talking about buying massive amounts of gold coins, and knowing people who did, that gold is not true wealth when times are hard.  He told us about Germany in World War II and how people would come down the country roads and see a farm with a garden, and they would come up to the door of a farm house and they would knock on the door.  When the farmer would come to the door, they would offer to buy food with gold and they were sent on down the road.  The man said three times “the garden was worth more than the gold” and this has stuck with me.  “The garden was worth more than the gold.”  We need to have food in the ground; we need to have gardens, orchards, vineyards, olive yards, bees, goats, chickens, and cattle.  We need to have meat on the hoof and crops in the ground."</para>
    
    <para>(---Jerry Diamond, Copied from a 2010-10-29 post to the Sustainable Cedar County Group, used with permission; originally
        from <link xlink:href="http://www.howtogetoutofbabylon.com/ebook/sectionone.htm">How To Get Out of Babylon</link>)</para>
    
    </section>
    
    <section><title>The Plan For Food In Missouri</title>
    
    <para>So, keeping that in mind, the <emphasis>first order of any plan for food in Missouri is to make more of it</emphasis>. If we are not producing enough food then there will not be enough to eat, let alone store.</para>
    
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>Grow more food. Explode small farm development, urban gardening, seed banking and livestock
            breeding. In the interests of returning to minimum production levels quickly, concentrate on:</para>
            <orderedlist>
            
            <listitem><para><link linkend="ThreeSistersGardening">Three-Sisters Gardening</link> (corn, squash, beans).
                <glossterm baseform="three-sisters garden">Three-sisters gardens</glossterm> require the least tilling
                and care on newly cultivated land, provide a mix
                of nutrition and easy to store vegetables.</para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>hardy free-range small livestock (e.g. goats, primitive sheep breeds, chickens, pigs).
                Free-range livestock gather their own energy from currently non-productive land and can be
                ramped up quickly with minimal infrastructure.
                Meat, eggs, dairy, wool, light draft, and leather production can be obtained depending on animal
                and breed.</para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>systems of aquaculture and vermiculture (e.g. barrelponics) to recover energy from agricultural
                waste and food scraps.
                These can provide high-production vegetables, animal feed, and soil enrichment to transform worn-out
                dirt back into fertile soil</para></listitem>
        </orderedlist></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>Revitalize farmers' markets, especially growers' markets, producers' cooperatives, CSAs, and mechanisms to market and distribute local food.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Rebuild our food processing infrastructure: mills, silos, canneries, butchers, dairies, and packing facilities utilizing local food.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>Store <link linkend="Salt">salt</link> locally against hard times (as it is one of the few life critical substances for both humans and livestock we cannot readily produce). We are talking about individuals storing amounts of salt for their own consumption but also communities and groups storing pallets-worth of salt for communal use. Salt also becomes a trade commodity to obtain things we do not have and critically need.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>Increase personal and local storage of food to give greater depth to our food supply
            and allow us to weather sustained emergencies.
            Right now, many of us would go hungry if supplies were cut off for even days or weeks.
            Encourage individuals and families to start small but start somewhere.
            Rebuild the community infrastructure to store food (e.g. granaries) against hard times.
            For personal and community food storage, we are recommending preservation of dry goods using dry ice
            in plastic food-grade buckets and barrels<citebiblioid>905</citebiblioid>.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>Educate people to cook using raw and stored foods, to do their own canning and preserving
            to have control over their own food supply and give them options in an emergency.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>Due to the current <emphasis>complete lack of infrastructure in Missouri for storing, milling,
        and processing grain</emphasis>, a critical component of local and personal food storage will depend
            on sprouted grains and legumes--- safe storage of grains and legumes, easy home sprouting techniques,
            use of sprouts in cooking and bread-making--- this will allow us to have a "Store what you eat and eat
            what you store" food supply as quickly as possible. The
            <link xlink:href="http://chetday.com/kiss.html">KISS Survival Food System</link> lays this out in a compact,
            simple way.</para></listitem>
        
    </orderedlist>
        
    </section>
    </chapter>
