<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" type="xml"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
        xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" status="draft">
    <info>
        <title>The County Restoration Handbook</title>
        <subtitle>Building the future one county at a time</subtitle>
        
        <authorgroup>            
        <editor>
            <personname><firstname>Eric</firstname><surname>Vought</surname></personname>
            <affiliation><shortaffil>Regional Co-Coordinator, Founding Member, The Well-Fed Neighbor Alliance</shortaffil></affiliation>
            <affiliation><shortaffil>President, The Statesmen For Our Constitutional Republic</shortaffil></affiliation>
        </editor>
        <editor>
            <personname><firstname>Cathi</firstname><surname>Vought</surname></personname>
            <affiliation><shortaffil>Regional Co-Coordinator, Founding Member, The Well-Fed Neighbor Alliance</shortaffil></affiliation>
        </editor>
        </authorgroup>
        
        <pubdate>2010-11-12</pubdate>
        
        <publisher>
            <publishername>The Well-Fed Neighbor Alliance</publishername>
            <address>
                <city>Springfield, MO</city>
                <country>United States</country></address>
        </publisher>
        
        <edition>0.1.1</edition>
        <releaseinfo>0.1.1: Minor revisions to 1st Major Printed Draft</releaseinfo>
        <revhistory>
            <revision>
                <revnumber>0.1.2</revnumber>
                <date>2010-11-12</date>
                <revremark>Incorporated online changes to Food. Incorporated online Family Emergency Plan article.</revremark>
            </revision>
            <revision>
                <revnumber>0.1.1</revnumber>
                <date>2010-11-12</date>
                <revremark>Editorial corrections to Legal Notice, Acknowledgements, Forward, Handbook Organization. Added
                bridgeheads to forward. Moved external links (URLS) to footnotes so as not to be
                confused with citations.</revremark>
            </revision>
            <revision>
                <revnumber>0.1</revnumber>
                <date>2010-11-06</date>
                <revremark>1st Major Printed Draft</revremark>
            </revision>
        </revhistory>
        
        <abstract>
            <para>This project is a collaboration between the Well-Fed Neighbor Alliance,
                The Statesmen For Our Constitutional Republic, and other organizations.
                The goal of the handbook is to provide a guidebook and framework for restoring the sovereignty,
            good stewardship, stability, and general resilience  of the counties of the United States, starting with
            Lawrence County, Missouri, as our initial focal point. Sovereignty is the focal point of this effort:
            none of the other terms we use: good stewardship, stability, and resilience, make sense outside the
            context of local people having control over their own lives.</para>
  
            <para>None of this is intended to imply that a locality can or must isolate itself from the rest of the
                country or the world. Each locality, however, can and must be prepared to provide its most critical
                needs for itself, when it must, during all kinds of emergencies or crises.
                A locality must also have alternatives for any of its basic needs, even those it traditionally
                provides for itself.
                Without being able to provide for its own needs, neither a community nor its individuals have autonomy
                nor control over their own destinies: you cannot successfully negotiate for anything when you cannot
                walk away from a bad deal.</para>
            
            <para>The Lawrence County document is meant to be heavily tailored for different localities.
                Clearly Greene County, MO, Tioga County, NY, Los Angeles County, CA, and Pima County, AR
                have very different needs and must meet them differently.
                No single effort can hope to cover all these diverse needs, but many ideas and best practices can be
                shared.</para>
            
            <para>The Handbook is a compendium of knowledge developed in an online shared-authoring environment at
            http://countyrestorationhandbook.thestatesmen.org. Periodic snapshots are published from the online information.</para>
        </abstract>
    </info>
    
    <xi:include href="legalnotice.xml"/>
    
    <preface><title>Preface to 0.1</title>
    <para>This is a partial draft with useful information as a demonstration of where we are headed.
    Much is missing, especially parts of the Cyclopedia and Glossary which are online. The Bibliography is very
    rough. But a tremendous amount of material has come together and perhaps it is a good beginning. ---Eric Vought</para>
    
    </preface>
    <xi:include href="forward.xml"/>
    
    <xi:include href="acknowledgements.xml"/>
    
    <part xml:id="IntroductionAndOrganization">
        <title>Introduction and Organization</title>
        
        <xi:include href="handbookorganization.xml"/>
        
        <xi:include href="starthere.xml"/>
        
        <xi:include href="wherearewenow.xml"/>
        
        <xi:include href="levelsofdetailoverview.xml"/>
        
        <xi:include href="levelsofneedoverview.xml"/>
    </part>
    
    <part xml:id="LevelsOfDetail">
        <title>From Family and Farm to County- Levels of Detail</title>
                
        <xi:include href="familyfarmlevel.xml"/>
        
        <xi:include href="communitytownshiplevel.xml"/>
        
        <xi:include href="countylevel.xml"/>
        
    </part>
    
    <part xml:id="LevelsOfNeed">
        <title>From Economic Restoration To Simple Survival - Levels of Need</title>
        
        <xi:include href="townshipselfreliance.xml"/>
        
        <xi:include href="emergencymanagement.xml"/>
        
        <xi:include href="disasterpreparation.xml"/>
    </part>
    
    <part xml:id="Food">
        <title>Food</title>
        
        <xi:include href="foodoverview.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="salt.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="workingwithwholegrains.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="foodseedsgarden.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="threesistersgardening.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="foodstoragesupplies.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="smalllivestock.xml"/>
    </part>
    
    <part xml:id="Communications">
        <title>Communications and Neighborhood Organization - What Ties It Together</title>
        <xi:include href="communicationsoverview.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="resilientcommunications.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="ruralwatcharea.xml"/>
    </part>
    
    <part xml:id="RestorationCyclopedia">
        <title>Restoration Cyclopedia - Topics From A to Z</title>
        <xi:include href="alternativeenergyandlighting.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="aquaponics.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="bugoutbag.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="clothing.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="childrenandelderly.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="emergencyflashlights.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="familyemergencyplan.xml"/>
    </part>
    
    <glossary></glossary>
    
    <xi:include href="bibliography.xml"/>
    

    
    <index>
        <title>Index</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>castle defense</primary>
            <see>security and defense</see>
        </indexterm>
    </index>
    
    <appendix xml:id="SupportingDocuments">
        <title>Supporting Documents</title>
        <para></para>
    </appendix>
    
</book>
