<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="SmallLivestock">
    <title>Small Livestock</title>
    
    <indexterm zone="SmallLivestock">
        <primary>livestock</primary>
        <secondary>small</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    
    <para>Land that is marginal for planting is often initially overlooked by people trying to produce their own food. Small livestock can be incorporated into a sound agricultural plan very easily, often providing additional benefits beyond simply supplying milk, eggs and meat.</para>
    
    <para>When we first moved to our farm, the weeds were overtaking most of the property and the bugs were horrible. By introducing sheep and chickens, we were able to not only eliminate these problems, but actually gain from them; the weeds kept the sheep eating for weeks, and the chickens had a field day with the variety of bugs around the farm.</para>
    
    <para>There are benefits and drawbacks to all types of livestock, however a large number of the drawbacks can be avoided by using primitive or heritage animal breeds. As an example, we have raised Shetland (primitive) and Suffolk (improved) sheep in the past. The only real benefit of the Suffolks are their fast weight gain; one of the original animals in the breed record books put on as much as 45 pounds in the first eight weeks of age. By comparison, the Shetlands, though they lack the quick weight gain of the Suffolks, are hardier, do not have serious issues with parasites, do not have birthing problems, have better instincts with regards to predators, do not have serious hoof issues, and do well on otherwise marginal forage. The Suffolks we have raised, on the other hand, have required a large amount of intervention to keep them healthy; this costs the owner both time and money. This includes tail docking. The Shetlands are born with naturally short tails, whereas the Suffolks have been bred to produce as much wool as possible, and were therefore bred to have longer tails; in warmer climates, this can cause a nasty complication called flystrike, because of waste being kept close to the body and allowing flies to become problematic. To say that it is disturbing is putting it mildly; if you want to investigate flystrike on your own, I wouldn't suggest it after meals unless you have an extremely strong stomach.</para>
    
    <para>One of the simplest ways to start with livestock is to raise chickens. These small birds require little more than food, water, shelter and protection from predators. There are literally hundreds of plans for chicken tractors, which are basically a small protected (fenced) pasture, roosts and nesting boxes in a small, portable structure. It is easy to raise between four and twenty chickens in a chicken tractor, with the larger end requiring mechanical assistance (i.e., ATV, tractor, truck, horse, etc.) to move it. The tractor is moved every few days to provide fresh pasturage for the birds to find new insects and seeds to eat. Among the dual-purpose breeds I can recommend are Rhode Island Reds, Buff Orpingtons, Barred Plymouth Rocks and Araucanas; these birds do fairly well on range, produce both meat and eggs and are fairly hardy as they have been bred for multiple purposes, and so have not lost the good genetics from either extreme. You can raise hens to produce eggs without a rooster; however, if you want to raise chicks, you will need one of the "country alarm clocks".</para>
    
    <para>Chickens can also be free-ranged, with a coop to put them up in at night; you may, however, have predation losses during the day from hawks and dogs. We have often raised 20% more chicks than we will need in layers to account for these losses. We did lose many more than that once when we had one of the neighboring field that they hung out in brush-hogged; this removed almost all of the cover they had available to be able to hide from hawks. Well, they say hindsight is 20/20; hopefully our loss will be your gain.</para>
    
    <para>When bringing young chicks home, you will need to set up a brooding area; this should include a boundry to keep them contained, heating lamp, litter, waterer and feeder. If it is not in an enclosed room, you may want to add a cover on the top. We use a quart waterer for up to six chicks or a gallon for more, a small rectangular feeder, sawdust or wood pellet litter, place it all in a large plastic tote (sans the lid, of course!) and top it with 1/2" hardware cloth and a reflector "trouble" light with a 40-75 watt bulb - we often just rest the lamp on top of the hardware cloth. There is a small matter of adjustment with the light; if the chicks are all gathered together underneath it, they are not warm enough - you will need to either lower the light closer to them or put a higher wattage bulb in. In contrast, if they are crowding each other out of the shadows, it is too warm and the bulb should be raised or replaced with a lower wattage bulb. A lady I knew some years back had a clever way of getting around using electricity, as she was living very remotely; she set up a hook on the bottom of the cover and hung a small kerosene hurricane lantern on the hook, adjusting the flame until it was the proper temperature for the chicks. Eventually you will be able to do away with the lamp as they grow in their adult feathers; keeping track of how close or far they are from the heat source will help guide you in this.</para>
    
    <para>Once you have the chicks home, you will want to dip their beaks in the water so that  they understand where to find the water. I usually do this by taking the chicks out of their transport box one at a time and doing this as I put them into the brooder; that way you are sure to have done it with each chick.</para>
    
    <para>If you bring home laying hens or older pullets that do not need the heat lamp, or if you are moving chicks you have raised into a coop, you will need to keep them in the coop for three days; this helps them recognize this as "home". Your coop will need one square foot of floor space per bird, or eight square inches for bantams (this is a type of miniature chicken). You will also need to provide one nesting box for every four layers you have; these can be about ten to twelve inches wide and about a foot deep, with fresh bedding (we use straw or hay) and the lowest one being ten to twenty inches from the floor. Chickens prefer to lay in private, dark areas, so you will want to put the nesting boxes in the darkest part of the coop. Roosts should be provided as well; these boards or branches are one to two inches in diameter and allow the chickens to sleep above the floor; this keeps them from roosting in the nesting boxes, which can create extra work in upkeep.</para>
    
    <para>Other possibilities in the poultry arena are Guinea hens, ducks, turkeys and geese. Guinea hens are helpful if you have serious insect problems; however, they are wilder than chickens and you will often find them roosting in the trees instead of their coop. Ducks are just plain fun; they produce good (if somewhat large) eggs and meat, and their antics provide fun entertainment at times. In looking at turkeys, you will want to stay away from heavily "improved" genetics; the trend lately has been to produce a large, meaty breast, often to the detriment of the bird's health. Geese make wonderful watchdogs in the coop; they will not harass the chickens if there is adequate roosting space for the chickens to get off the ground, and anything that gets into the henhouse and shouldn't be there won't get out. Some geese tend towards aggressive, especially towards small children, but we have not had too much trouble with the African and Toulouse breeds we have raised.</para>
    
    <para>Rabbits are another easy-to-manage livestock. A breeding trio of rabbits (two does and a buck) from a good local breeder will give you a good start into small meat production. I recommend setting up a colony cage or room; this allows the rabbits to interact and lowers the monitoring needed to establish a breeding time. I have seen fine setups with five-gallon buckets turned on their side for nesting boxes, a good bit of straw on the floor for them to "dig" in, watering crocks or bottles, and freely available feed or good quality hay.</para>
    
    <para>Pigs are a bit unique in livestock circles; they are omnivore monogastrics that cannot process cellulose fibers. They can be fed a large variety of food, from kitchen scraps to garden leavings to grain and mixed feeds. They put on weight fairly readily without a lot of cost. However, their tendency to root means that their fencing must be fairly tight and in good condition; many a homesteader has enclosed a pig where they intend to start a garden within a couple of years, and let the pig do their tilling for them. It should be noted that because of their diet and digestive system being closer to ours, their manure must be composted more extensively before being used in food gardens, in order to remove pathogens that can infect humans.</para>
    
    <para>Sheep are a particular favorite of mine; they produce beautiful fiber (though there are hair breeds available if you have no use for that), lean meat and non-polluting lawn mowing. They are often easier to handle than larger animals, especially the smaller primitive breeds.</para>
    
    <para>Both sheep and goats grow to their full size in about a year's time, providing relatively quick turn-around and a carcass that is of a good size for a family to butcher and process. They are also very social animals and do not do well alone.</para>
    
    <para>Sheep and goats are different in that sheep cannot tolerate the amount of copper in their diet that other livestock can take; also, when threatened, sheep tend to band together and run away from danger, whereas goats separate and turn to face the danger. This can really confuse a good herd dog that will spend all day trying to get behind the goat to drive it while the goat spends all day trying to keep the dog in front of it!</para>
    
    <para>Goats are nature's escape artists; an individual posted on a forum that he had gotten a couple goats at auction, what type of fencing did he need? A well-experienced goatherd repled, "Watertight." I am of the opinion that if your goats have not gotten out in a week or so, the fencing is either (finally!) goat tight, or they're plotting their next escapade. They do provide good milk, though you will want to make sure bucks are downwind of the does at milking time; otherwise you may get a musky taste to your milk.</para>
    
    <para>Dehorning of sheep or goats is a matter of personal choice; I prefer to leave them intact as it will provide them additional protection from predators. There are a variety of methods to dehorn an animal, from pastes to irons to surgical techniques, that all have their advantages or disadvantages. Along the same lines is tail docking and castration of males (wethering). There are various tools for crushing or cutting the tail or testicles. We use an elastrator, which is a small, strong rubber band that can be stretched using a tool, slipped over the area in question, and released. Though the lambs or kids will show discomfort for the first few minutes, they are usually up and around within a half hour, and are back to themselves by the next day.</para>
    
    <para>This brings up another item: veterinary care. Contrary to popular belief, most farmers do not have a veterinarian come out for standard animal health care. Most mammals receive a minimum vaccination of a tetanus shot; this can be purchased at most feed stores. We usually give our tetanus shots a few weeks before birth, as this will provide protection to the young as well as the mother, and then again at weaning (at which time we wether the rams we do not want to keep as breeding stock). After that, we give a yearly booster; the ewes receive it before they give birth every year, and the rams and wethers receive theirs at the same time. Vaccines are not at all difficult to administer; a simple subcutaneous shot involves lifting up a fold of skin, swabbing with alcohol or iodine, sticking the needle and pushing the plunger. Intramuscular shots are somewhat more difficult as you need to be aware of meat cuts that could be damaged; however, finding a place just behind the "armpit" of the animal usually works well, and the only change is that you will need to draw back on the plunger; if blood appears in the syringe, you will need to find another place to vaccinate as you have found a blood vessel.</para>
    
    <para>Another thing we deal with both at this time and again in the fall is trimming hooves, easily done with a pair of pruners or a pocketknife, to remove the excess growth in the hoof that has folded over underneath the foot. We keep our animals on somewhat rocky pasture, so we only trim twice a year, and usually only the six-month-old lambs need it in the fall. At the same time, we check for parasites using the FAMACHA method, which looks at the color of the <link xlink:href="http://goat-link.com/content/view/110/107/">inner eyelid</link> to determine if an animal is anemic; if so, we will treat with a dewormer, rotating types if the parasites seem to be resistant to a particular formulation.</para>
    
</chapter>
