<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="ThreeSistersGardening">
    <title>Three Sisters Gardening</title>
    
    <indexterm zone="ThreeSistersGardening">
        <primary>gardening</primary>
        <secondary>three-sisters</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    
    <para>A three sisters garden is a traditional Native American planting system that allows for companion planting, lower inputs and better nutrition.</para>
    
    <para>By planting corn, beans and squash together in hills, we provide a better environment for the plants we grow than we could accomplish by planting separately. This is known as companion planting. This allows each plant to both contribute and benefit from the other two plants. Corn uses a lot of nitrogen in the soil; beans fix nitrogen into the soil for the corn to use. Beans often require a support to climb in order to be productive; corn provides this support. Squash uses some of the nitrogen and provides a natural mulch of large leaves, covering a good portion of the hill and preventing competitive weeds from becoming well established, as well as keeping the soil cool and moist during the heat of summer.</para>
    
    <para>There is also the benefit of a lower input requirement for these types of plantings. Hill culture practices requires only a small amount of ground be tilled, with the squash being allowed to spread out over the ground between the hills. The beans take the place of fertilizer applications, the spiny squash leaves keep animal pests away and the corn plants eliminate the need to build trellises for the beans. In addition to labor savings, there is also a lower cost to bring the crops to harvest because of decreased fertilizer and materials purchases.</para>
    
    <para>The three plants also provide a generally complete nutrition. The corn grain provides carbohydrates; the squash provides vitamins and oils in the seeds; and the beans provide protein.</para>
    
    <para>To plant a three sisters garden, in late spring (after the chance of frost has passed) you will need to clear a hill approximately three feet wide and mounded one foot tall. If you are planting multiple hills, try to keep the centers of the mounds four to five feet apart. You will also need to select appropriate varieties of seeds. The corn will need to be a fairly tall variety, not a miniature type. The beans will need to be pole beans, so that it would climb the corn. The squash needs to also be a vining variety, so that it will spread out over the ground rather than forming bushes; also, you may use either summer or winter squash varieties. We've had good luck here with butternut squash, Cherokee Trail of Tears beans and a Hopi variety of corn that is great for cornmeal.</para>
    
    <para>Once your garden has been turned, plant six or seven corn seeds about six inches apart in a circle near the middle of the hill. After a week or two, when your corn is four or five inches high, plant six or seven bean seeds about six inches apart from each other and also from the corn plants. At the same time, plant four squash seeds near the edges of the hill.</para>
    
    <para>After the plants are growing well (three to four inches), thin the plants down to the strongest four corn plants, four bean plants and one to two squash plants. You can use the bean plants as sprouts in sandwiches or salads.</para>
    
    <para>The corn can be harvested while it's in the green corn stage, when the silk is dry and dark brown, and then roasted or boiled like sweet corn; otherwise allow it to stay on the plant into autumn when it is dried on the stalk and ready for storage. Beans can also be harvested throughout the season to eat cooked like green beans, but also can be allowed to dry on the vine for use over the winter as dry beans for soups or baked beans; we usually harvest ours during the summer and then allow a good amount to dry on the vine for the next year's seed. Summer squash can be harvested as they reach their full growth, but winter squash should be allowed to remain on the vine until the skin hardens thoroughly in the fall, and then cut the vine three or four inches from the squash. We regularly store winter squash for several months (usually through the winter) in a cool back room in our house.</para>
    
</chapter>